<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The essence and unitie of the Church Catholike visible, and the prioritie thereof in regard of particular churches discussed. / By Samuel Hudson minister of the Gospell.</title>
            <author>Hudson, Samuel, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86681</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3265</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E271_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212195</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99870841</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99870841</idno>
            <idno type="VID">123237</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86681)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 123237)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 45:E271[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The essence and unitie of the Church Catholike visible, and the prioritie thereof in regard of particular churches discussed. / By Samuel Hudson minister of the Gospell.</title>
                  <author>Hudson, Samuel, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Miller for Christopher Meredith at the signe of the Crane in Pauls Churchyard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March 8th 1644"; the 5 in imprint date is crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church --  Catholicity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:123237:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ESSENCE AND UNITIE OF THE Church Catholike VISIBLE, And the Prioritie thereof in regard of Particular Churches Diſcuſſed.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Samuel Hudſon</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>George Miller</hi> for <hi>Chriſtopher Meredith</hi> at the Signe of the Crane in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:123237:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:123237:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader, this <hi>Theſis</hi> was compiled about a yeare agoe, for the accommodation of private friends, and was not intended by me for publike view, yet ſince, at the deſire and by the approbation of ſome whom I much reſpect, I am induced to conſent to the publiſhing of it. I confeſse the texture of it is more homely, and the ſtile more incompt then will pleaſe the tender eyes and delicate eares of this dainty criticall age. But they that handle controverſies muſt endeavour to ſpeake in proper and ſignificant words, and deale by ſtrength of proofes and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and not ſtand upon neatneſſe, or labour to deck their lines with flowers of Rhetorick. I acknowledge this question is an unuſuall ſubject and therefore but little trodden before me; and hath many paths that croſſe it, more frequently beaten, which did ſomewhat blunt mine intention, and diſſwade me from making of it publike, even after I had yeelded thereunto. For first I finde the ſubject of my question much questioned, yea, flatly denied by many Divines of great worth both Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, French, and Germane, who affirme that there is no Church Catholike viſible, but that the Church Catholike is the inviſible Church only. But there having come divers tractates out lately which have touched that ſubject, and prove a Church Catholike viſible, eſpecially <hi>Gulielmi Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonii, Conſideratio quarundam Controverſiarum, &amp;c.</hi> by command and allowance of the Walacrian Churches (ſome few ſentences whereof I have added hereto) and <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Prinn</hi> his truth triumphing over Falſhood, &amp;c. I was the more confirmed that this is no private opinion, or ſtrange heterodoxie, but a firm
<pb facs="tcp:123237:3"/>
truth, and therefore I was the more encouraged to divulge it.</p>
            <p>And for the predicate of the queſtion it is ſeldome met withall, eſpecially ſtated in theſe termes, and thoſe that ſtate it ſo, make the particular Churches to be the prime Churches, which I have endeavoured to refute according to my light.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the queſtion lyeth at the root of divers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies and differences that are now abroad, I was willing to lend what light I could to the ſame. Mine intention is not to provoke or exaſperate any, but if any ſhall receive any benefit hereby I have mine aime, and let God have the Glory. But if any ſeem contentious about it, I cannot anſwer in <hi>Paul's</hi> words,<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.16.</note> 
               <hi>We have no ſuch cuſtome, nor the Churches of God,</hi> For the cuſtome is every where now to contend and quarrell about every part of Divinity, and he is no body that cannot carp at, and wrangle againſt one truth or other, ſo that all our practicall Divinity is turn'd into Polemicall, and the power of godlineſſe runs out into diſputes, and thoſe truths which formerly ſeemed moſt firme, plaine, and ſmooth, are now by the crotchets of mens braines runne into ſuch diviſion, and become ſo knotty and prickly, that a man knowes not where to faſten on them, or how to hold them, but he ſhall prick his fingers with one thorny objection or other. For my part I am not ſo inamoured on, or wedded to mine owne opinion, but if any can convince me of errour, I ſhall be willing to retract it, and embrace the Truth of God, or if any can afford any further light into this ſubject I ſhall be glad to ſee it, and bleſse God for it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recommendation">
            <p>I Have peruſed this Diſcourſe, and finding that it handles a queſtion of great importance, and diſcuſſeth it with Judgement and Moderation, I doe commend it to the Preſſe, hoping that the intelligent and impartiall Reader may receive Benefit; and Peace and Unitie in the Church be furthered by it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Edm. Calamy.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="thesis">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:123237:3"/>
            <head>THE ESSENCE AND VNITY OF THE CHURCH CATHOLIKE Viſible, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>QUEST.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Vtrum Eccleſia viſibilis univerſalis ſit prima vel orta?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR the handling of this queſtion, here are theſe foure tearmes to be opened. Firſt, What is meant by <hi>Church?</hi> Secondly, What by <hi>Viſible?</hi> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, What is meant by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall?</hi> Fourthly, What by <hi>prima</hi> and <hi>orta?</hi> Firſt, What a Church is? The word Church, is taken in a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill or a theologicall ſenſe: In a <hi>civill</hi> ſenſe, for a company of people ſummon'd or gathered together for ſome civill affaires: ſo even the rout met together, <hi>Acts</hi> 19. is called <hi>Eccleſia,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in a <hi>theologicall</hi> ſenſe, it ſignifieth a company of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that are called, or to be called and joyned together, ſtanding in ſome ſpirituall relation to God. And ſo the word is taken diverſly.</p>
            <p>Firſt and moſt properly, for the <hi>whole company of the elect,</hi> as they are oppoſite to reprobates, whether Jew or Gentile, and in this ſenſe it is taken, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.25, 26. <hi>As Christ loved the Church and gave himſelfe for it, that he might cleanſe it, with the waſhing of water by the word.</hi> So <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1.18. <hi>His body the Church.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:123237:4"/>
Interdum cum Eccleſiam nominant eam intelligunt quae reverâ eſt coram Deo, in quam nulli recipiantur niſi &amp; adoptionis gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ filij Dei ſunt, &amp; Spiritus ſanctificatione vera Chriſti mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra. Ac tunc quidem non tantum ſanctos qui in terra habitant comprehendit, ſed electos omnes qui ab origine mundi fuerunt.</hi> Calvin <hi>Inſtit. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>ſect.</hi> 7. where you may ſee more of this ſubject. Of theſe there are three ſorts: The firſt are <hi>elect un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called,</hi> which are not actually the Church, but <hi>in potentiâ;</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part are <hi>militant,</hi> warring with principalities and powers, with the fleſh, world and Devill, being juſtified and ſanctified per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: the third part are <hi>triumphant</hi> in Heaven, having finiſhed their courſe, and are now <hi>the spirits of just men made perfect.</hi> For the fourth ſort which the Papiſts make, <hi>viz.</hi> Eccleſia <hi>dormiens</hi> in Purgatory we acknowledge not.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The word <hi>Church,</hi> ſometimes ſignifieth more then the elect, <hi>viz. the multitude of beleevers, whether truly or in ſhew only.</hi> So <hi>Acts</hi> 8.3. Saul <hi>made havock of the Church,</hi> Acts 12.1. Herod <hi>stretched out his hand to vex certain of the Church.</hi> Now it is certain, that neither <hi>Herod</hi> nor <hi>Saul</hi> knew who were elect, but as himſelfe expounded it, <hi>He perſecuted this way unto the death. And he deſired letters to</hi> Damaſcus, <hi>that if he found any that way he might bind them.</hi> So <hi>Acts</hi> 5.11. <hi>Fear came upon all the Church.</hi> Now it cannot be conceived that they were all elect that feared that judgement of God. So 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.16. <hi>Let not the Church be charged with them, that it may relieve wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes indeed.</hi> Now we cannot conceive, that only the elect gave collection, but the whole number of profeſſours, which yet are called the Church. <hi>In Eccleſia plurimi ſunt permixti hypocritae qui nihil Chriſti habent praeter titulum &amp; ſpeciem,</hi> Calv. <hi>Inſt. li.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>ſ.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                  <hi>Tearme.</hi>
               </note>The ſecond tearme to be opened is, what is meant by <hi>viſible?</hi> The Church is diſtinguiſhed into <hi>viſible and inviſible,</hi> which yet are not two diſtinct Churches, or ſpecies of Churches, but it is a diſtribution of the Subject by the Adjunct, <hi>viz. à duplici modo communionis, externo &amp; interno.</hi> Such as have ſpirituall commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Chriſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> inwardly, are ſaid to be <hi>inviſible</hi> mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, which are only known to God and not men, having this ſeale, <hi>the Lord knoweth who are his;</hi> Such as have externall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:123237:4"/>
in outward ordinance <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they are called <hi>viſible</hi> members, becauſe their communion is viſible and apparent. Now only the inviſible company have communion for life, and are elect, many of thoſe that have externall communion, and are viſible members ſhall periſh. And yet by reaſon of their profeſſion, are ſaid (2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.1.) <hi>to be in God the Father, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>Ames</hi> alſo confeſſeth. Such was the Church of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth</hi> and <hi>Epheſus,</hi> &amp;c, wherein all were not in communion for life. And of ſuch Chriſt ſpeaketh, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.2. <hi>Every branch in me that beareth not fruit he takes away.</hi> Theſe are ſaid to be <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.1. <hi>Denying the Lord that bought them.</hi> And <hi>ſanctified,</hi> Heb. 10.29. <hi>And hath accounted the bloud of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant wherewith he was ſanctified, an unholy thing.</hi> And in <hi>Pauls</hi> exordiums of his Epiſtles: <hi>To the Church of God, to them that are ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, called to be Saints,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.2.</p>
            <p>Now we are to know that this diſtinction of <hi>viſible</hi> and <hi>invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible</hi> is a <hi>very lame</hi> one, and the lameneſſe thereof <hi>deceiveth</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: for whereas all diſtinctions or diſtributions ſhould have their parts diſtinct, and different, and the more oppoſite the members thereof be, the better the diſtribution is; theſe two branches of this diſtinction interfere one with another, and the one compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends the other: <hi>the viſible comprehend the inviſible</hi> here in this world, I meane the perſons though not the notions. For <hi>though indeed every viſible member is not inviſible, yet every inviſible member is alſo viſible.</hi> They that have inward communion with Chriſt for life, are not taught and nouriſhed only by an inward unction or inſpiration, but are faine to have externall communion alſo in the outward ordinances of God. <hi>De Eccleſia vivorum modò agitur cui Symbolum Apoſtolicum praeſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt non de coeleſti. Ramus in Symb.</hi> So that this diſtinction is like the old diſtinction of <hi>gratia gratis data, &amp; gratia gratum faciens,</hi> whereas <hi>omnis gratia gratum faciens, eſt etiam gratia gratis data.</hi> If inviſible had been taken for Saints in Heaven, and viſible for Saints on earth, it had been a compleat diſtinction. Or if viſible had been taken for a Church conſpicuous, flouriſhing with liberty of ordinances, and inviſible for a Church latent, as under perſecutions, and generall hereſies, then it had been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat; but the tearmes are not uſed in either of thoſe ſences, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:123237:5"/>
therefore the diſtinction halteth. So that in what is to be ſaid, we muſt take heed that by viſible we meane not only ſuch as are hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites and reprobates, but thoſe that are alſo truly godly: not only ſuch as make externall profeſſion of faith, whereby they are differenced from heathens,<note place="margin">What a Church vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible is.</note> but ſuch as have inward ſincerity alſo, whereby they are differenced from hypocrites. <hi>The Church vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible is, a company of people called by God from Idols to the true Religion, and profeſſing ſubjection to that call,</hi> which is true of the godly as well as the hypocrites.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                  <hi>Tearme.</hi>
               </note>The third tearme to be opened is <hi>(univerſall.)</hi> We are to know that the Church of God admits of ſeverall diſtinctions from ſeverall accidents. As in reference to <hi>the time</hi> wherein the Church hath or doth exiſt, it is diſtributed into the Church <hi>under the old Teſtament,</hi> and the Church under the <hi>New.</hi> And this is diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted againe, into the <hi>primitive</hi> and <hi>ſucceſſive.</hi> So in regard of the <hi>places</hi> where the Church doth exiſt, or perſons of whom it conſiſteth, it receiveth the diſtinction of <hi>univerſall</hi> and <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</hi> Now in this queſtion, univerſall is meant principally in regard of
<list>
                  <item>Perſons,</item>
                  <item>Places,</item>
               </list>
and not in regard of time. <hi>The Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick exiſting on earth at the ſame time, is compared with par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches exiſting at the ſame time alſo.</hi> Univerſality is applied to places and perſons in the Church at the ſame time.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall viſible Church is.</note>
               <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall viſible Church, is the whole company of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible beleevers throughout the whole world.</hi> Severall men give ſeverall deſcriptions thereof. I ſhall ſet down ſome of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eccleſia Dei vivi eſt columna &amp; firmamentum veritatis to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to orbe terrarum diffuſa propter Evangelium quod praedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſicut dicit Apostolus in omni creatura quae ſub coelo eſt.</hi> Aug.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sancta Eccleſia nos ſumus, ſed non ſic dico nos, quaſi ecce qui hic ſumus, qui me modò auditis, ſed quotquot ſunt Chriſtiani fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deles in univerſo terrarum orbe, quoniam à ſolis Ortu uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad occaſum laudatur nomen Domini. Sic ſe habet Eccleſia Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica mater noſter.</hi> Aug. <hi>Serm.</hi> 99.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eccleſia eſt congregatio ſanctorum in quâ Evangelium rectè docetur &amp; rectè adminiſtrantur Sacramenta.</hi> Aug. conf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saepè Eccleſiae nomine univerſam hominum multitudinem
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:123237:5"/>
in orbe diffuſam deſignamus quae unu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe Deum &amp; Christum colere profitetur.</hi> Calv. Inſtit. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Est Congregatio omnium per orbem univerſum qui conſentiun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in fide Evangelica.</hi> Bulling.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eſt coetus hominum Chriſtum ſuum negem, ſacerdotem, &amp; prophetam profitentium.</hi> Keckerman.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In novo Testamento, vocamus Eccleſiam pro omnibus qui Chriſto nomen dederunt.</hi> Zuinglius. <hi>Vniverſa multitudo Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianorum quae ſe fidelem cenſet ſimul <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nus fidelis populus, una Eccleſia dicitur.</hi> Idem.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eccleſia ſignificat totam illam omnium multitudinem quae generatim exvocatione, &amp; profeſſſione externa aeſtimatur.</hi> Trelc.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eccleſia eſt viſibilis coetus amplectentium Evangelium Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti, &amp; rectè utentium Sacramentis.</hi> Gerard.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Statuimus Eccleſiam quandam univerſalem externam per to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum orbem diſperſans, nobis in ſacris literis deſcribi, quae viſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li quadam politia unicum Eccleſiaſticum Organicum corpus conſtituit, ſub quo omnes Eccleſia particulares Claſſicales Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciales &amp; Nationales tanquam partes totius continentur.</hi> Apollon. 29. pag.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> &amp; quandocun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fuerint homines Apoſtolicâ fide informati, Chriſtianam Electorum rempublicam conſtituunt, etiamſi disperſi in omnes Orbis partes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sic</hi> Antoninus <hi>Philoſophus Civem Romanum dixit eſſe qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Romanis legibus viveret. Ita quicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Chriſtianis legibus moribuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vivit, ubicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſit, nihil intereſt, civis est Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, &amp; ad publicum de regendâ civitate Dei conſilium adhiben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, ut Eccleſiae Catholicae diſciplina Catholica ſit.</hi> P. Ramus <hi>de Eccl. Cathol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sometimes, ſaith <hi>Bifield,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Church ſignifieth a company of men in one City or Province, that did outwardly profeſſe the true Religion, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.18, 22. And ſo uſually in the writings of Divines, the company throughout the world, ſo profeſſing, is called the viſible Church. <hi>Bifield</hi> on <hi>Art.</hi> 9."</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Catholick in the moſt evident ſenſe agreeth to the Church now under the Goſpell, ſince the partition wall betweene Jewes and Gentiles was broken down, and yet in ſome ſenſe it may agree to the Church from the beginning. <hi>Idem.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:123237:6"/>For particular Churches, either ſingle or combined, either Nationall, Provinciall, Claſſicall, or Congregationall, it is not belonging to this Queſtion to diſcuſſe the Quaeries about them, and therefore I ſhall only ſet down ſome deſcriptions of them poſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as they are uſually taken by others, and give you my preſent ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A Nationall Church.</note>
               <hi>A Nationall Church is where all the viſible, publike, religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Aſſemblies of a Nation, being parts of the Church Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, living under one politick, civill Government, are by the profeſſion of the ſame faith, and communion in the ſame worſhip and Government, united into one body Eccleſiaſtick, or Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiasticall Republike.</hi> Two things, as I conceive, are required to make a Nationall Church. Firſt, Nationall agreement in the ſame faith and worſhip. Secondly, Nationall Union in one Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall body in the ſame community of Eccleſiaſtical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Churches in <hi>France</hi> and the <hi>Netherlands</hi> have the ſame faith and worſhip, and kind of Government, but they are not in the ſame Nationall community thereof<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Apollo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>p.</hi> 29.</note>. See proofes for Nationall Churches under the Goſpel, Iſai. 55.5. <hi>Thou ſhalt call a Nation which thou knewest not, and Nations which knew not thee ſhall runne unto thee.</hi> It is ſpoken of Chriſt under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel: and there is ſet down, both <hi>Gods call of a Nation,</hi> and a <hi>Nations anſwer to that call,</hi> and there can be no more required to make a Church. Alſo, Iſai. 19.25. <hi>Aegypt my people,</hi> Aſſyria <hi>the worke of my hands, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>mine Inheritance.</hi> Where all thoſe three Nations are called three ſiſter Churches, in effect, if you marke the coherence. It is a prophecy of Goſpell times, Pſal. 22.27. <hi>All the ends of the world ſhall turn unto the Lord, and all the kinreds of the Nations ſhall worſhip before thee,</hi> Revel. 11.15. <hi>The kingdoms of this world, are become the kingdoms of the Lord, and of his Chriſt.</hi> Alſo, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.11. and 86.9. And by the ſame reaſon when a part of a Nationall Church ſhall joyne in particular conſociation and community in a City or Province, or Claſſis, they may receive denomination from thence: the one containing a greater part of the Church Catholike, the other a leſſe. For the Church Catholick being a <hi>ſimilar body</hi> retaines the name <hi>(Church)</hi> in what parts, parcels, or quantities ſoever it be divided into, for convenient community, untill it be brought
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:123237:6"/>
               <hi>in minimum quod ſic.</hi> as the Philoſophers ſay, <hi>i. e.</hi> into the leaſt parts that can enjoy publike communion in ordinances, which is a particular congregation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gerſom Bucerus in diſſert. de gub. Eccleſ. p.</hi> 11. hath this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of a particular Church, <hi>Nos particularem Eccleſium intelligimus quemlibet credentium caetum in unam vocationem Divinam, Evangelij praedicatione, ſacrarum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> inſtitutionum obſervatione, adunatum, ac uni Presbyterio ſubjunctum, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cros verò conventus uno aut pluribus locis agitantem. Nam pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roeciarum in quibus convenitur numerus, accidenturia res eſt, nihil ad Eccleſiae particularis eſſentiam pertinons.</hi> Now this ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to me to be a deſcription of a Presbyteriall or claſſicall Church, and ſo not to divide the Church Catholick into any leſſe parts for enjoyment of all the uſuall publike ordinances, eſpecially of ſome parts of diſcipline and ordination, then a Presbyteriall Church.</p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cotton</hi> tels us, that a <hi>viſible Church is a myſticall body, whereof Chriſt is the head, the Members Saints, called out of the world, and united together into one Congregation, by an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Covenant, to worſhip the Lord, and to edifie one another in all his holy Ordinances.</hi> But (with due reſpect to ſo grave and worthy a man) this ſeemes to me to belong to an <hi>inviſible Church,</hi> not a <hi>viſible,</hi> becauſe the matter thereof is the myſticall body of Chriſt, conſiſting only of Saints called, not only from <hi>Idols,</hi> but out of the <hi>world,</hi> and therefore truly godly. Neither dare I make a particular explicit holy Covenant to be the <hi>forme</hi> of a particular Church, as this definition doth, becauſe I find no mention of any ſuch covenant, beſides the generall covenant, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on Churches, nor example or warrant for it in all the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and therefore cannot account it an ordinance of God, but a humane politick device to keepe the members together, which in ſome places and caſes may haply be of good uſe, ſo it be not urged as an ordinance of God, and ſo it be not uſed to inthrall any, and abridge them of liberty of removall into other places and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations for their convenience. Or urged as the forme of the Church. And for the enjoyment of all the Ordinances of God in one congregation, it ſeemeth to me very <hi>inconvenient</hi> for ſome of the Ordinances, and altogether <hi>impoſſible</hi> for others.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:123237:7"/>Firſt, It is <hi>inconvenient,</hi> and of dangerous conſequence, that a Church conſiſting of 7, 10, 20, or 30. ſhould paſſe the formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable ſentence of Excommunication againſt any perſon, to caſt him out of communion, not only with themſelves, but the whole Church Catholike viſible, and deliver him up to Satan. For if it be inflicted by the votes of the whole congregation, as ſome would have it, many of the Members being private men, and haply altogether illiterate, or unexperienced, through want of age, education or parts, are not able to underſtand the nature of the allegations and probations, they may be ſo intricate, or not able to apply the rule unto the caſe, for inflicting of a juſt cenſure, and may be in danger to beare particular favour, or ill will unto their perſons, and ſo apt to be ſwayed by love, pity, or hopes from them, or to be over-awed by feare or threatnings, being poore men, ſervants, children, work-men tenants, and therefore our brethren for congregationall Churches, have of late, ſeeing this inconvenience, debarred the people from votes, and put it into the hand of the Elders onely<note n="*" place="margin">See M <hi>Cottons</hi> book ſet out by M. <hi>Goodwin</hi> &amp; M. <hi>Nie.</hi>
               </note>. Yea even the Elders of one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation may be in danger of the ſame temptations, becauſe of particular relations, and their dependance on them for mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; but ſuppoſe they were as free as Angels from temptations or infirmities, which they are not, yet the weightineſſe, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity of the cenſure require to be performed by a colledge of Elders, of a combined Presbytery, that ſo it being paſſed not by the votes of 3, or 4. onely, and they lyable to ſo many temptations alſo, but by the joynt conſent of a greater Presbytery, free from any ſuch temptations or exceptions, may be done with the more advice, and combined authority, and be more dreadfull to the party, and be the better accepted, and ſubmitted unto, without heart burning, and grudge againſt the particular Elders, or fear of revenge.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is <hi>impoſſible</hi> for one congregation to enjoy all the Ordinances of God within themſelves. Firſt, Synods and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels are acknowledged to be the ordinance of God, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly by that reverend Divine M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cotton,</hi> in a late booke ſet out by him, and he groundeth it on <hi>Act.</hi> 15. And though ſome of our brethren for congregationall Churches wave that place, yet grant the thing, and are members of one at this time, and this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:123237:7"/>
all men will grant, cannot be had in one congregation, but ſometimes requires the helpe of a whole Province, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, yea many Kingdomes. Yea ſecondly, the Ordinances that nearly concerne a particular congregation cannot be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by that alone: for how can a congregation of private Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, try the ſufficiency of an Elder to be elected over them, and if they have a tryed man among them, who ſhall give him impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of hands, which is belonging only to Elders to performe. Neither have our Brethren of congregationall Churches ever da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (as farre as I have heard) to permit common Chriſtians to impoſe hands on their Elders, but alwayes deſired the Elders of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther congregations to doe it, and therefore they cannot have this Ordinance among themſelves. And though this ſeeme to ſome a thing of ſmall weight, yea but a<note n="*" place="margin">Quiſquiliae veritatu ſunt pretioſiſſimae.</note> complement, yet is it an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God: And the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2. reckoneth it up amongſt the <hi>Principles of Religion,</hi> and part of the <hi>foundation;</hi> which place <hi>Hen: Jocob</hi> urgeth vehemently to overthrow the lawfulneſſe of all the Miniſters of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> becauſe they have (as he conceived) erred in the <hi>foundation,</hi> not having right and due impoſition of hands of the Presbytery, though, by his leave, he was miſtaken, for thoſe that impoſed their hands on them were <hi>Presbyters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this impoſſibility befals a Church, either in the beginning of it, and firſt conſtitution, or may, at other times by mortality of Elders, or when but one remains alive, which will be frequent.</p>
            <p>And becauſe it is not rationally probable that the Churches of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, Rome, Corinth, Philippi, Theſſalonica,</hi> or the 7 <hi>Churches of Aſia</hi> were <hi>meerly congregationall,</hi> but rather <hi>Presbyteriall,</hi> unles it were in their very infancy for a little time before their numbers were increaſed. It ſeemeth difficult to me to find in Scripture an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe inſtance or example of a congregationall Church, ſtanding and continuing ſo by it ſelfe. The Church of <hi>Cenchraea</hi> mentioned, <hi>Ro.</hi> 16.1. is the moſt probable, becauſe of the conceived ſmalneſſe of the place, yet it is not certaine, for it was a Port Town<note n="*" place="margin">Oppidum Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthiorum na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vium ſtatione c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leberrimum, et ideò frequent val<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulorum. <hi>Gualr.</hi> in <hi>Rom. 16.</hi>
               </note>, and yet it may be, the neceſſity of thoſe times, and disjunction from other places might make it ſtand ſingle for a while at leaſt. And yet there might be more congregations then one therin, if it were ſo popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as ſome ſay.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:123237:8"/>Indeed we find, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.34. theſe words, <hi>Let your women keepe ſilence in the CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCHES,</hi> which word <hi>(Churches)</hi> if it doth import ſeverall companies meeting in ſeverall places, to enjoy the publike Ordinances, and that theſe companies are called Churches, (which is to ſome a Queſtion) yet it is certain they were all one combined Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> often ſpoken of in the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar number.</p>
            <p>But this diſpute belongs not to this Queſtion, yet the preſent difference of opinions and practiſes have cauſed me to dilate a little upon this ſubject, beyond the explication of the Tearme. And I underſtand by particular Churches, any, or all the fore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Churches, whether <hi>Nationall, Provinciall, Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall,</hi> or <hi>Congregationall:</hi> and this laſt principally: for thoſe that have firſt mooved this Queſtion, meane principally, if not ſolely, the congregationall Church, becauſe (as I ſuppoſe) they hold no other particular Churches, but ſuch.</p>
            <p>The fourth Tearme to be opened is, What is meant by <hi>Prima vel Orta.</hi> This diſtinction, or at leaſt in theſe tearmes, is not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, for M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Parker in hic Politeia Eccl.</hi> was the firſt that ſprung it, as farre as I know.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Primum</hi> in Logick is defined to be, <hi>Quod est ſuae Originis. Ortum quod oritur à primo.</hi> But I ſuppoſe in this Queſtion it is meant, which hath the priority in conſideration. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in our apprehenſion of Churches we are to begin at the Church Catholike and deſcend to particular Churches, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at the particular Churches, and aſcend to the Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike. Which notion is firſt in diſtinct knowledge, whether <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia univerſalis, aut particularis?</hi> Which is as the root, which the branches? Which is as the mother, which the daughter? Or to ſpeake more punctually: Whether the nature and priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Church belong firſt to the particular congregation, and ſo aſcend to the Church Catholike, or belong firſt to the Church Catholike, and deſcend unto the particular Churches?</p>
            <p>I do not in this Queſtion by <hi>primum</hi> meane <hi>abſolutè primum,</hi> for God only is <hi>Eus primum,</hi> who hath his being in himſelfe, and from himſelfe, and giveth being to all his creatures: And ſo the whole Church is Gods houſe, built by him; but, <hi>Primum in ſuo genere in genere Eccleſiarum.</hi> Neither doe I meane by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:123237:8"/>
               <hi>Ortum,</hi> that the particular Churches doe ariſe out of the generall by the ſole vertue or innate power and ſtrength of the Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, but becauſe the particular Churches are made up of the members of the Church Catholike, and partake of the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits and priviledges of the Church primarily, not becauſe they are members of the particular Churches, but of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.</p>
            <p>And yet I deny not but that a Miniſteriall, Synodicall or Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicall Church, made up of delegated Members of divers particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Churches, <hi>pro tempore</hi> (which ſome improperly call a repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative Church) may put on the notion of <hi>Eccleſia Orta,</hi> and the particular Churches, out of which thoſe members are choſen and delegated, may in ſome ſence, in reference unto them put on the notion of <hi>Eccleſia prima,</hi> but the Queſtion is not ſo ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but between the whole Church Catholike, and whole parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches.</p>
            <p>Now I have opened the Tearmes of my Queſtion, I find two Queſtions inſtead of one, and whether of them is the moſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, I cannot tell. For whereas the ſubject of every Queſtion uſeth to be taken for granted, and the predicate only proved, I find the ſubject of my Queſtion exceedingly oppoſed, and that by our own Divines; and therefore I muſt crave leave to confirme that ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently, or elſe whatever I ſhall ſay of the predicate, will be as a houſe built on the ſand, or a caſtle in the aire; <hi>For if there be no univerſall Church viſible, then it is not capable of being</hi> prima, <hi>or</hi> Orta.</p>
            <p>In handling both theſe Queſtions, I ſhall follow my wonted method. I preferre one divine teſtimonie, before ten arguments, and one good argument before ten humane teſtimonies.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, <hi>Whether there be a Church Catholike viſible?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I know that our Divines in anſwer to the <hi>Pontificians</hi> doe deny the Church Catholike to be viſible, as <hi>Zanchy, Gerard, Whita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, Chamier</hi> and <hi>Ames</hi> againſt <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and <hi>Sadeel</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Turrianus.</hi> But the <hi>Pontificians</hi> ſtate not the queſtion, as I ſtate it, and I confeſſe their aſſertions of the Church Catholike to be falſe. For,</p>
            <p>Firſt, They take <hi>viſible</hi> for <hi>conspicuous, glorious</hi> and <hi>manifeſt, ſpecious</hi> and <hi>flouriſhing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:123237:9"/>Secondly, They hold that the name <hi>Catholike Church</hi> belongs to one Church, viz. <hi>The Church of Rome,</hi> and that being the Church Catholike, and comprizing the univerſality of the Church in it ſelfe, all that will be members of the Church Catholike muſt ſubmit to them, and be members of that Church.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, They hold that it is neceſſary that this viſible Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church ſhould be under one viſible univerſall head, which they make to be the Pope, Chriſts Vicar Generall, and in theſe regards our Divines doe contradict and confute them. But there are paſſages enough in our Divines writings, that may be brought to allow and approve <hi>viſibility, aſpectability</hi> and <hi>unity</hi> in all the Churches of the Saints throughout the whole world. I will give you a taſte, but of one of the fore-mentioned, for brevity ſake, and he the moſt rigid in diſcipline, and exact in Logicall diviſions and deductions of any of them, and that is D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Ames,</hi> who in his <hi>Medulla</hi> ſaith: <hi>Eccleſia nunquam de ſinit eſſe viſibilis.</hi> Which cannot be meant of any particular Church, for that may faile. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, he ſaith, <hi>Congregationes illae particulares ſunt quaſi partes ſimilares Eccleſiae Catholicae, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> adeo &amp; nomen, &amp; naturam ejus participant.</hi> And further ſaith, <hi>Illi qui profeſſione tantum ſunt fideles, dum remanent in illa ſocietate, ſunt membra illius Eccleſiae, ſicut etiam Eccleſiae Catholicae, quoad ſtatum exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</hi> And in his Bellarminus <hi>enervatus,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Nos fatemur Eccleſiam militantem viſibilem eſſe quoad formam accidentalem, &amp; externam, in ſuis partibus &amp; ſingulatim, &amp; conjunctim, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now though I have ſet downe theſe humane teſtimonies firſt, yet it is not that I meane to leane upon theſe as my maine proofes, but only to ſhew that our Divines in denying the Popiſh tenet of a Church Catholike viſible in their ſence, yet all of the fore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned deny it not in my ſenſe, if any doe.</p>
            <p>But for proofe that there is a Church Catholike viſible, I will firſt give you <hi>Scripture,</hi> and ſecondly <hi>demonſtration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>Scripture,</hi> ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 8.3. Saul <hi>made havock of the Church.</hi> I ſhewed you before that this muſt needs be a viſible Church, for they could not elſe be perſecuted, and certainly <hi>Saul</hi> could not diſcerne the inviſible company, but perſecuted promiſcuouſly <hi>all that were of that way;</hi> neither was it a particular Church, for this perſecution was in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and in <hi>every Synagogue, and to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:123237:9"/>
Damaſcus, and even to ſtrange Cities.</hi> So that by Church here is meant, <hi>an indefinite number of viſible Churches or Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations,</hi> which were in no other community but profeſſion of the ſame faith; <hi>and an indefinite, is equivalent to a generall,</hi> and by the ſame reaſon that the word Church would reach all theſe Churches, it would reach all the Churches in the world.</p>
            <p>The ſame word there is, <hi>Galat.</hi> 1.13. <hi>I perſecuted the Church of God, and waſted it:</hi> and yet it is ſaid when he was converted, <hi>then had the Churches reſt throughout all Judea, and Galileo, and Samaria,</hi> which yet were but ſome parts of the <hi>Church</hi> (in the ſingular number) which he perſecuted.</p>
            <p>Againe, See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.32. <hi>Give no offence to the</hi> Jew, <hi>nor Gentile, nor to the Church of God:</hi> Where the word <hi>Church,</hi> cannot ſignifie the elect only, nor any one particular Congregation, or Kingdome, but <hi>indefinitely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See alſo, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. <hi>God hath ſet ſome in the Church, firſt Apoſtles, ſecondarily Prophets, thirdly Teachers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Church there ſpoken of, is <hi>not the triumphant Church, nor the Inviſible Church only,</hi> for they were viſible meſſengers, and ſome of them but only viſible, for <hi>Judas</hi> had obtained part in the Apoſtleſhip and Miniſtry, and was ſent to preach and work mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles: and many Prophets were not of the inviſible number, <hi>for many ſhall ſay, Lord, Lord we have prophecied in thy name,</hi> and yet ſhall not be ſaved. But to be ſure they were ſent to afford the Saints viſible communion in ordinances.</p>
            <p>Again, This is <hi>not meant of the Church Entitive,</hi> which is a ſimilar, and (as I may ſay) an <hi>homogeniall body,</hi> every mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber being equall, and of the ſame capacity, as a member, but of <hi>the Church organicall,</hi> a
<list>
                  <item>Heterogeniall</item>
                  <item>Diſſimilar</item>
               </list>
body, becauſe here are ſet downe the officers. <hi>Neither is here meant a particular Church,</hi> but all collectively that were within the bounds of the Apoſtles commiſſion, which was the Church in the whole world, <hi>Goe teach all Nations, &amp;c.</hi> and all the Churches that have Paſtors and Teachers over them, which all the Churches in the world have, or ought to have, and yet all theſe are called but <hi>one Church, one body, verſ.</hi> 20. Now <hi>if there be officers of the Church Catholike viſible, then there is a Church Catholike viſible, but the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:123237:10"/>
Prophets and Evangeliſts, were officers of the Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike viſible,</hi> for they had no limits, and yet are ſaid to be ſet, <hi>not in the Churches, but in the Church.</hi> And this is granted by our brethren for Congregationall Churches, that they were officers of the Church Catholike, and therefore did not baptize into particular Congregations, or in refernce to them, but into the generall. And this <hi>Cartwright in his Catechiſme</hi> granteth, concerning the Church Catholike. Now certainly they were not officers to the true beleevers only, ſeeing they cenſured others alſo.</p>
            <p>Alſo 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Theſe things I write unto thee, that thou mayeſt know how thou oughteſt to behave thy ſelfe in the houſe of God, which is the Church of the living God.</hi> This Church muſt be a viſible Church, where he and others muſt exiſt, and converſe together, and carry themſelves in mutuall duties. Now theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections concerned not <hi>Epheſus</hi> alone, or in any ſpeciall manner, but all the Churches where ever he ſhould come. It is that Church which is the ground and pillar of truth, which holdeth it forth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to others <hi>more forenſi,</hi> which is the Church Catholike, unto which <hi>Timothy</hi> was an Evangeliſt.</p>
            <p>Againe, It is the Church viſible, that is ſo often in the Scripture called the <hi>Kingdome</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Mark. 4.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 30. Luk. 7.28.</note> 
               <hi>of God, and the Kingdome</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Mat. 13.24, 31, 33, 44, 45, 47.</note> 
               <hi>of Heaven:</hi> Chriſt calls them <hi>not Kingdomes, but the Kingdome,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares this Kingdome, <hi>to a field of wheate mingled with tares,</hi> and himſelfe expounds it, that <hi>the field is the world,</hi> and this muſt be the Chriſtian world: for the other is a field of tares only; for <hi>verſ.</hi> 41.<note place="margin">Mat. 13.41, 49.</note> it is ſaid, they ſhall gather out of the Kingdome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In this field, particular Churches are but particular ridges, enjoying the ſame tillage,<note place="margin">Sever the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the juſt.</note> ſeed, fencing, watering.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is a barn floore with wheate and chaffe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is a draw net gathering together good and bad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is a marriage where were wiſe and fooliſh virgins, ſome with wedding garments, ſome without, ſome had oyle, and ſome had none but lamps of profeſſion.</hi> Now theſe metaphors cannot be limited to any particular Congregation, but agree to the Church Catholike, not as inviſible but viſible.</p>
            <p>And when we ſay, <hi>Thy kingdome come,</hi> we pray for the good of the Church Catholike viſible, that it might be enlarged and have freedome and purity of ordinances, which are things that concerne it as viſible.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:123237:10"/>In 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24. it is ſaid, <hi>Then ſhall Chriſt deliver up the Kingdome to God his Father:</hi> This is <hi>not the eſſentiall King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> which he hath with the Father and Holy Ghoſt as God, for that he ſhall never deliver up. Neither is it <hi>the kingdome of grace</hi> which he exerciſeth in the hearts of the elect, for that ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue for ever, and be more perfect in Heaven. For the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of grace here, and glory afterward, differ only <hi>gradu com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munionis,</hi> as <hi>Ames</hi> tells us, here the degree is imperfect, then it ſhall be perfect both in graces and joyes. <hi>But it is the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome exerciſed in the viſible Church, in ordinances of worſhip and diſcipline,</hi> which ſhall then ceaſe: for as the Evangelicall externall ſervice, thruſt out the legall and ceremoniall, ſo ſhall the heavenly thruſt out the evangelicall.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28. <hi>Wherefore we receiving a kingdome which cannot be moved, let us have grace whereby we may ſerve God acceptably, with reverence and godly feare.</hi> This kingdome cannot be meant of the <hi>internall kingdome of grace</hi> in the heart, for that was alſo exerciſed by Chriſt in his peoples hearts, in the old Teſtament, but it is meant of the externall ordinances of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and diſcipline, which differed from that under the Law: elſe the Apoſtles antitheſis of the Church under the Law; and the Church under the Goſpell had not been good, which are the things he compares in that place. Now nothing is oppoſite to externall under the Law, but externall under the Goſpell. It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be meant of the <hi>kingdome of glory,</hi> for they had not yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it: and it is plaine he ſpeakes of a Kingdome wherein we may <hi>now ſerve God acceptably, with reverence and godly feare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Repent for the Kingdome</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 3.2. Mat. 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>of Heaven is at hand. He that is leaſt in the Kingdome</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Mat. 1.11.</note> 
               <hi>of Heaven is greater then John.</hi> Now if theſe things were ſpoken of a particular congregation only, which particular congregation in the world ſhall impropriate theſe things to it ſelfe? But if true of everyone in particular, and all in generall, and theſe all be continually called one kingdome, then there is a Church Catholike viſible.</p>
            <p>Againe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12. The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>What have I to doe to judge thoſe that are without.</hi> The prepoſition <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>extra,</hi> I deſire to know what Noune ſhall be underſtood or ſupplied unto it. Is it not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, without the Church? And can we
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:123237:11"/>
think that that Church was the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> only? Had <hi>Paul</hi> nothing to doe to judge any that were out of the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> when he was an Apoſtle all over the Chriſtian world? This could not be meant of the inviſible company only; What had <hi>Paul</hi> nothing to doe to cenſure any but inviſible memmbers? Why did he then excommunicate <hi>Hymineus, Philetus, Phygel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, Hermogines</hi> and <hi>Alexander?</hi> And ſaith, <hi>I would they were cut off that trouble you:</hi> and therefore it muſt be meant of the Church Catholike viſible. What have I to do to judge thoſe that are <hi>without the pale</hi> of the Church? they are not under my power or cognizance, but belong only to the civill Magiſtrate. And we uſually ſpeake of the countries that are within the pale of the Church, and thoſe that are without. And we have an axiome, <hi>Extra Eccleſiam non eſt ſalus,</hi> which cannot be meant of any particular congregation in the world, but is true of the Church Catholike viſible, typified by the Ark of <hi>Noah,</hi> without which or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily, and viſibly, there is no hope of ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Alſo it is ſaid, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.47. <hi>God added to the Church daily ſuch as ſhould be ſaved;</hi> which was not a particular congregationall Church but the Catholike. <hi>For it is not probable that thoſe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and twenty that were together at Pentecoſt, were one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregationall Church, for many of them were men of Galilee,</hi> which by their habitation could not pertaine to the Church in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and yet the reſt were added to them.</p>
            <p>Againe, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.10. <hi>To the intent that unto the principalities and powers in heavenly places, might be known by the Church, the manifold wiſdome of God.</hi> This Church here ſpoken of, was not a particular Congregation, but the whole Church Catholike whereof <hi>Paul</hi> was made a Miniſter, as he ſaith in the ſame chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And this proficiency of the Angels (for ought I know) was by the truths which it pleaſed God by the miniſtry of the word to make knowne audibly to the Church.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.21. <hi>To him be glory in the Church throughout all ages, &amp;c.</hi> This place ſpeakes of the Church Catholike viſible in the largeſt ſence that can be poſſible, both in reſpect of place, for it is the whole Church by which God hath glory, which is uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall: and time, for it is the Church in all ages, but no particular congregation, nor nationall Church can be ſure to laſt to all ages,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:123237:11"/>
no not by ſucceſſion, but the Church Catholike ſhall.</p>
            <p>Againe <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.4, 5. The Apoſtle proveth the Church to be but one by divers arguments. Firſt he ſaith, <hi>There is but one body</hi> of Chriſt, which is therefore called <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.6. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> both of Jewes and Gentiles, <hi>i. e.</hi> the ſame body. Secondly, there is <hi>but one Spirit</hi> in that whole body, which is as one ſoule in one body. Thirdly, there is but <hi>one hope of their calling.</hi> Fourthly, there is but <hi>one Lord</hi> or King over the whole Church. Fifthly, there is but <hi>one Faith, i. e.</hi> one Religion, Doctrine, Worſhip, the ſame Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and Statutes for all. Sixthly, There is but <hi>one Baptiſme</hi> to admit into this Church. Now if the whole world were under one King, and governed by one Law, and all capable of the ſame Priviledges, and all made Denizons by the ſame way of inrowle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; it would make but one Empire, yet ſo it is with all the Churches in the world, they have the ſame King, Law, Word, Sacraments, of admiſſion, and nutrition, which they viſibly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject themſelves unto, and receive, therefore they are all one viſible Church.</p>
            <p>Againe, Chriſt ſaith <hi>on this rock</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Matth. 16.18.</note> 
               <hi>will I build my Church, and the gates of hell ſhall not prevaile againſt it.</hi> Was this a particular Congregation? No ſurely, but the Church Catholike, for any particular Church may be prevailed againſt, but the whole ſhall not. The place is meant of a Church <hi>future,</hi> to be built, which Chriſt then intended to ſet up, which was <hi>the Evangelicall Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church,</hi> and not Catholike as ſome take it for the Church paſt, preſent, and to come, for thoſe paſt were already built, and were in Heaven out of Gunſhot of aſſault, but it is meant <hi>de Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia vivorum, de militante, de Eccleſia quam Chriſtus erat aedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficaturus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> O but this place is meant of the Church inviſible, for they that are only viſible may be prevailed againſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true, but thoſe inviſible are alſo viſible, and they ſhall never be prevailed againſt as viſible. <hi>Eccleſia nunquam deſinit eſſe viſibilis.</hi> Satan or perſecutours ſhall never ſo far prevaile as to cut off all the viſible members. And though ſuch hereſies come that ſhall deceive all but the Elect, yet as long as the Elect are not deceived, there remaines a Church Catholike viſible ſtill in their viſibility. If all the viſible members ſhould faile, then all
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:123237:12"/>
the inviſible muſt needs faile alſo, for none are inviſible in this world but be muſt be viſible alſo: except any be converted and fed only by inſpiration, which we have no ground for in the Scripture.</p>
            <p>Again, Excommunication in 2 <hi>Ep. John</hi> 10. is called <hi>caſting out of the Church.</hi> What Church is that? It cannot be the Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church, for all the cenſures in the world cannot caſt a man out of that, if once he be in, therefore it is the viſible Church; and if it be the viſible Church, then I would know, whether a man truly excommunicated in one Church or Congregation, is not thereby excommunicated from brotherly fellowſhip with all Congregations? Or whether the delivering up to Satan be only within the bounds of one Congregation, ſo that if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move out of ſuch a <hi>circle</hi> or <hi>circuit</hi> of ground to another, he is out of Satans bonds againe, and may communicate there ſafely? I deny not but that through ignorance ſuch a thing may be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but certainly if the cenſure be paſt againſt him, he needeth no other Excommunication, but his firſt ſentence will binde him in all the Chriſtian world, if it can be known. I am not ignorant that I have D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Whitakers,</hi> and many Proteſtant Divines againſt me herein, and therefore I onely propoſe what my light guideth me to judge herein. Herein I agree with <hi>Apollonius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sicut per excommunicationem legitimam excommunicatus non tantum ex hac vel illa particulari Eccleſia ejicitur, ſed ubicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum ligatur, &amp; excommunione fraterna univerſalis Eccleſiae ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluditur, Matth.</hi> 18.17, 18. <hi>Ita &amp; per Sacramentum Baptiſmi &amp; ſacrae Euchariſtiae homini communio Eccleſiaſtica non tantum in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulari ſed, &amp; univerſali Eccleſia obſignatur. Apollon. p.</hi> 26.</p>
            <p>If any one that is <hi>called a</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 5.11.</note> 
               <hi>brother,</hi> be a drunkard, railer, extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner, &amp;c. What makes him to be called a brother? Is it becauſe he is of that particular Congregation, or the Church Catholike? Is it becauſe he is an inviſible member, or a viſible by Profeſſion? Few Fornicators, Idolaters, Drunkards, &amp;c. are inviſible mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</p>
            <p>Againe, all thoſe Metaphors which ſet out the Church in Scripture, ſhew the unity of the Church Catholike. This is the <hi>woman</hi> clothed with the Sunne,<note place="margin">Rev. 12.1.</note> the Righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, and the Moon, all terreſtriall mutable things under her feet: or clothed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:123237:12"/>
with the Sunne, the purity of Doctrine, and the Moon, i. <hi>e.</hi> (as ſome will have it) Diſcipline under her feet. Surely this woman was not a particular Congregation, but the Church Catholike: for were it meant of particular Congregations, it ſhould have been <hi>women, not a woman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There ſhall be <hi>one Shepherd,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, and <hi>one Sheep-fold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 10.16.</note> which is meant of the Church Catholike, and that viſible, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of Jew and Gentile.</p>
            <p>The Church is called <hi>the Body of Chriſt,</hi> and that is the Church Catholike, for Chriſt hath but one body. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.5. <hi>As we have many members in one body, and all members have not the ſame office: ſo we being many are one body in Chriſt, and every one mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers one of another.</hi> This the Apoſtle ſpeakes of the viſible, Orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall Church, for thereupon he fals to reckon up the ſeverall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices in the Church, as <hi>Prophecying, Teaching, Exhorting, Giving, Ruling, Shewing mercy,</hi> which ſome compute to be an exact di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution of the Church Offices. So <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.4.<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.17. 1 Cor. 12.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 13, 20. Eph. 2.16.</note> It is called <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1 Tim. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>Houſe of God. How thou ſhouldeſt behave thy ſelfe in the Houſe of God. And the City of God</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Eph. 2.19. Heb. 12, 22. Rev. 3.12.</note>. Now theſe things had they been meant of particular Congregations, ſhould have been <hi>Bodies, Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Cities, Sheepfolds.</hi> But as many members in a body hinder not the unity of the whole, and many townes in a Kingdome, and many houſes in a Citie, and many roomes in an houſe, or in the Arke, hinder not the unity thereof: ſo many particular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, hinder not the unity of the Church Catholike. <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.9. <hi>My Dove, my undefiled is but one, ſhe is the only one of her mother.</hi> She is the <hi>Lilly</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Cant. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>among the thorns,</hi> which is the Church militant. She is called <hi>the Spouſe of Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Cant. 4.8, 9, 10, 11, 12.</note>. Yea, the Holy Ghoſt chooſeth to joyn many particular Churches together by Nounes collective, Nounes of multitude in the ſingular number, where it can be with convenience. Remarkeable is that 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 5.2. where writing to the ſtrangers ſcattered throughout <hi>Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Bithinia,</hi> he cals them all <hi>one flock,</hi> not flocks. <hi>Feed the flock of God which is among you.</hi> The ſame word <hi>Paul</hi> uſeth <hi>Acts</hi> 20. <hi>to the Elders of Epheſus. Eſt una ſola Chriſti Eccleſia, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ae ob id etiam dicitur Catholica. Particulares Eccleſia non ſunt impedimento quin una ſit Eccleſia. Zanch. de Eccleſia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond kinde of proofe hereof is by <hi>argument</hi> or <hi>demonstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:123237:13"/>
If particular Churches be viſible, there is a viſible Catholike Church; but particular Churches are viſible:</hi> therefore, The conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence will follow, whether you conſider the particular Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches as <hi>Species</hi> or as <hi>Partes. Omne particulare habet ſuum generale, ſive univerſale: &amp; omne membrum habet ſuum integrum, &amp; omnis pars habet ſuum totum.</hi> If therefore there be particular Churches, there is a generall, and if the particular be viſible, ſo is the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall; if the particulars be mingled, wheat and tares together, ſo is the generall. <hi>Genus &amp; Species, pars &amp; totum (ſimilare preſertim) ſunt ejuſdem praedicamenti.</hi> Ten thouſand particular corporeall ſubſtances cannot make one generall incorporeall. Ten thouſand viſible particular Churches cannot make one inviſible generall Church. But all Divines, yea, our brethren for Congregationall Churches, yea the Separation, hold that particular Churches are viſible, as conſiſting indeed of viſible members. And <hi>Gerard</hi> though he will not grant a Church Catholike viſible, yet ſaith, <hi>Eccleſias particulares viſibiles eſſe concedimus;</hi> and therefore he muſt grant the generall Church, to which thoſe particulars be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, to be of the ſame kinde.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> All that can be ſaid againſt the former conſequence (as I gueſſe) is, that though the particular Churches have exiſtence, yet the generall hath none, but only a notionall eſſence, and exiſt only in the particulars, as Animalitie exiſteth not by it ſelfe, but <hi>in homine &amp; Bruto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſw.</note>Anſwer, here were ſome colour in this objection, if you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Church Catholike onely as a <hi>genus,</hi> and the particular as <hi>ſpecies,</hi> yet not enough to amount to a deniall of a Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike viſible, no more then any Logician denyeth <hi>Animal,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no ſuch creature, but <hi>in homine &amp; bruto.</hi> But the proper notion of the Church Catholike, and particular, is of <hi>inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grum &amp; membra.</hi> And ſo as I ſaid before <hi>Ames</hi> in his <hi>medulla</hi> taketh it. <hi>Congregationes illae particulares ſunt quaſi partes ſimilares Eccleſiae Catholicae, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> adeo &amp; nomen &amp; naturam ejus participant.</hi> And then the argument ſtandeth thus. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi omnes partes exiſtunt ſimul compacta, ibi totum exiſtit; ſed omnes partes Eccleſiae Catholicae viſibilis existunt ſimul compacta.</hi> Therefore, The minor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> proved <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.16. <hi>From whom the whole body fitly joyned together and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacted by that which every joynt ſupplyeth,</hi> &amp;c. This place is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:123237:13"/>
of the Church militant, becauſe organicall, and organicall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the officers are there reckoned up, and Catholike, becauſe it is the Church to which Apoſtles, Prophets, and Evangeliſts are given. They have the ſame Lord, the ſame law, the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and have influence by love, ſympathy, and prayer into the wellfare one of another.</p>
            <p>For my part I conceive the Church Catholike to be <hi>Totum integrale,</hi> and the particular Churches to be <hi>ſimilares partes,</hi> and ſo members thereof, and parcels thereof, as the Jewiſh Synagogues<note n="*" place="margin">Jam. 2 2. 2 Theſ. 2.1. Heb. 10.25. <hi>Tilenus in theſ. part.</hi> 1. <hi>diſp</hi> 14. <hi>Theft.</hi> 3.</note> were of the Jewiſh Church, though with ſome more privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, for both Sacraments, &amp;c. and that every particular Church partaketh of part of the matter and part of the form of the whole. And theſe parts are limited and diſtinguiſhed from others, by civill and prudentiall limits for convenience of meeting, and maintenance, and tranſacting of buſineſſe: and that every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is a member of the Church in whoſe limits he dwels, being only in the generall Covenant of Baptiſme. And this member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is either divolved on him by Gods diſpoſing providence, by reaſon of his birth, or cohabitation there, or voluntarily aſſumed by his voluntary removall into that place allotted out by civill prudence for ſuch a particular ſociety to enjoy the Ordinances of God conveniently together. For he knew the Miniſter, and members, before he came in, or might have done, at leaſt, if he had pleaſed, and it is at his choice to remove out again, if he diſlike ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther officers, or members. But of any Chriſtian mans or womans dwelling in any City, or Towne, where there was a Church, and not to be a member of that Church, or to be a member of another Church in another town or city, and reſide in his own but <hi>per accidens,</hi> as ſome doe diſtinguiſh, hath neither example nor warrant in the Scripture. But ſeemeth to me to imply an unchurching thoſe places from whence they are gathered. As a man that comes to dwell in a towne ſhall thereby be a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of it, and ruled by the officers thereof in civill affaires, and if he like it not he may remove, and if they have any thing juſtly againſt him they may puniſh, or
<list>
                  <item>reſtraine</item>
                  <item>remove</item>
               </list>
him: ſo it is in the adminiſtration of Eccleſiaſticall juriſdiction. And as the limits of the particular ſeas, and their names are from the ſhoares and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:123237:14"/>
lands they are bounded by, though a heterogeneall body, ſo may particular Churches well be bounded by civill prudentiall limits though they ſeeme heterogeneall. We find frequently in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture The Church which was in <hi>Jeruſalem, Antioch, Corinth, Epheſus.</hi> Yea <hi>Cenchrea</hi> a port town ſome 8. miles from <hi>Corinth,</hi> gave name to the Church therein.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> If they be all one Church, it is neceſſary they ſhould all meet ſometimes together.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſw.</note>It is no more neceſſary then that all in a kingdome or empire ſhould meet ſometimes: it is enough that they are under the ſame King, and governed by the ſame lawes, and inſpired by the ſame Spirit, and walke in the ſame wayes, and tend to the ſame end, and fare the better for one anothers prayers; and rejoyce in the welfare, and mourne for the ill fare one of another, and help one another as they have opportunity. And yet we reade that many times the Church Catholike viſible hath met in generall Councels, by their delegates, or commiſſioners, as a miniſteriall Church Catholike, which in former times of the Church under Chriſtian Emperours was frequent, and there is no intrinfical let in the Church that they do not meet ſo ſtill, but only extrinſicall, and extraneous, by reaſon of the diviſions among the civill Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors, but even in our dayes a great part of this great body hath met in the Synod of Dort, by commiſſioners.</p>
            <p>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Whitakers and Apollonius</hi> acknowledge the meeting <hi>Act.</hi> 1. to be a generall Councell. The members were the Apoſtles who were Paſtours of the Church Catholike, and Brethren out of Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilee and Jeruſalem. The worke was to elect an Apoſtle who was to be a Paſtour of the univerſall Church: and they that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake and diſpatch a buſines which concernes the teaching and government of the whole Church muſt repreſent the whole Church Catholike. Yet there is ſo much power given to every Presbyteriall Church at leaſt, as may uphold it ſelfe, and exerciſe the diſcipline of the Church, for the being, and well being of it, ordinarily.</p>
            <p>Yet ſo as it is a part of the Church Catholike, into which alſo the cenſures there paſt, have influence, as ſhall be ſhewed more afterwards. And on ſome great occaſions there may be cauſe to fetch help further, as <hi>Cranmer</hi> appeald to a generall councell. But,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:123237:14"/>
if that extenſive power cannot be had, as now it is very difficult, then muſt that particular, nationall, provinciall, or Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Church reſt in that intenſive power that remaines within its owne limits. Yea even in a congregationall Church, if it ſtand ſo as it cannot combine with neighbours, or have recourſe unto them, it muſt be ſo: but that is an extraordinary caſe, and ſo not to be regulated by ordinary rules. And in ſuch caſes alſo all civill power muſt reſt in one congregation, as if it were in a wildernes where there were no neighbour townes or cities to which it might be joined: yet it followeth not that it muſt be ſo in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, or any other kingdome where there are counties, ſhires, cities, great townes, or a Parliament. Yea I know not but a particular family may, yea muſt be in ſuch an extraordinary caſe Independent, both in Eccleſiaſticall, and civill matters alſo, yet it followes not that there is any ſuch inherent right in every town or family all over the world, and that therefore particular towns and familyes in <hi>England</hi> are debarred of an inherent priviledge belonging to them, becauſe neceſſity may put ſuch an indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency on ſome, in an extraordinary caſe. As by Shipwrack, or being caſt into ſome Iland not inhabited.</p>
            <p>It is fit that a viſible Church Catholike here on earth ſhould <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> have a viſible head over them, that ſo the body and head may be of the ſame nature.</p>
            <p>This is the maine argument of the Pontificians for the ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy of the Pope,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> and that wich made our Divines deny them a Church Catholike viſible. But to the argument, I anſwer that the Church hath a head of the ſame nature, conſiſting of body and ſoule, who ſometimes lived in this kingdome of grace, in the dayes of his fleſh, and did viſibly partake in externall ordinances, though indeed now he be aſcended into his kingdome of glory, yet ceaſeth not to be a man, as we are, though glorifyed, and ceaſeth not to rule and govern his Church here below, for it is <hi>an everlaſting kingdome: Iſa.</hi> 9.7. As when King <hi>Iames</hi> was tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from <hi>Scotland</hi> to <hi>England,</hi> and lived here, he did not ceaſe to be King of <hi>Scotland:</hi> ſo neither doth Chriſt ceaſe to be the head of his Church, though he be tranſlated to his other kingdome of glory: and as for a vicar or deputy here below, it is not needfull. We confeſſe the government of the Church in regard of the head
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:123237:15"/>
is abſolutely monarchicall, but in regard of the officers it is Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craticall.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>4</label> Yea but the Church-Catholike cannot be viſible, becauſe it wanteth <hi>a proper exiſtence of its own,</hi> and exiſteth only in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence of particular Churches, on the members thereof? this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection is ſomewhat like a former, onely there, the exiſtence was ſaid to be in the <hi>Species,</hi> here, in the <hi>members.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſw.</note>So we may ſay of every aggregative body. A heape of ſtones exiſteth only in the exiſtence of particular ſtones: the whole e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement of water exiſteth only in particular dropps. By this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection you may deny particular viſible Churches, becauſe they exiſt not, but in particular families, and particular families exiſt not, but in particular members: but as I ſaid before, <hi>if the parts do exiſt, the exiſtence of the whole reſulteth thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An army exiſteth not but in the ſeverall brigades, and regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and they are billeted in diſtant places, and yet having one Generall, the ſame lawes martial, the ſame cauſe, the ſame ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, though they ſhould never be drawn up together into one body, yet are one army: So is the Church Catholike one, though it never meet bodily, becauſe <hi>the union is not corporeall,</hi> but an unity of profeſſion, of chief governour, of lawes, Spirit, way and hope. Yea the exiſtence of it will the more appeare, becauſe it hath priviledges belonging thereunto, which particulars have not, or but in part, and at ſecond hand, as ſhall be ſhewed in the ſecond queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>5</label> But that which you call the Church Catholike viſible may by perſecutions, warres, hereſies be brought into a very little roome, and haply to one congregation, or a few perſons.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſw.</note>It is poſſible, yet all the eſſence &amp; Priviledges of the Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike viſible are <hi>contracted</hi> and <hi>reſerved</hi> therein, and from them <hi>conveyed,</hi> and <hi>derived</hi> to thoſe whom they ſhall convert, and ſo ſhal dilate it ſelf again. And while the Church is but one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation, that, hath the notion of the Church Catholike more properly then of a particular Church. Yea though it be but in one family, as it was in the Arke in the dayes of <hi>Noah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Second Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note>I come now to handle the predicate of my Queſtion, which I may well call a ſecond queſtion, and that is: Which of theſe two Churches is <hi>Prima,</hi> and which <hi>Orta?</hi> Before I anſwer I deſire
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:123237:15"/>
you to remember, that the compariſon is not between the Inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the viſible Church, but between Churches of the ſame kinde, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Catholike viſible,</hi> and the <hi>particular viſible Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches:</hi> And then I anſwer, I conceive, the Church Catholike is <hi>Prima,</hi> and the particular Churches are <hi>Ortae.</hi> For</p>
            <p>Firſt, all the <hi>names</hi> that are in Scripture given unto the <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>1</label> Church viſible, agree primarily to the Church Catholike; ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darily to particular Congregations. As <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, we are firſt conſidered as called out from Idols, and devoted to be the Lords people, before we can be conſidered of this or that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation. And for priority of time, we know they were given to the people of the Jewes before ever any Congregationall Churches had exiſtence. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.38. The Church in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And the Jewes are frequently called the <hi>Lords people.</hi> So the Church is called the <hi>Houſe of the Living God.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. And <hi>the ground and pillar of truth. The Citie of God, Iſai.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Gods vineyard, John</hi> 15.1. wherein branches in Chriſt bearing no fruit are cut off.<note n="*" place="margin">John 10.16.</note> 
               <hi>Christs Sheepfold,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Matth. 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>Barn-floore,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Matth. 13.37, 38.</note> 
               <hi>Drag not, Wheat-field, Kingdome of Heaven, a great houſe wherein were veſſels even of diſhonour,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.20. Theſe names cannot be limited to, or impropriated by any particular Congregation, but are firſt true of the whole Church, and of every particular Church as a part thereof. I muſt here remember you againe of that ſaying of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Ames</hi> in his <hi>Medulla. Congregationes particulares ſunt quaſi par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſimilares Eccleſiae Catholicae at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> adeo &amp; nomen &amp; naturam ejus participant.</hi> Where he grants the Church Catholike to have the firſt right to the name, and nature of a Church, and the particulars only by participation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that is the primary Church to which the <hi>Promiſes</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>2</label> and <hi>Priviledges</hi> of the Church doe primarily belong: but the Promiſes and Priviledges of the Church doe primarily belong to the Church Catholike. Therefore, &amp;c. The minor I prove, becauſe the firſt Evangelicall Promiſe that ever was made in the world was to <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> repreſenting all mankinde, and therefore conſequently the whole Church of God. This was before there was any diviſion or diſtinction made of Churches into Jew, and Gentile, Nationall or Congregationall. Againe, the maine commiſſion for gathering the Evangelicall Church was gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:123237:16"/>
               <hi>Goe teach all nations and baptize them in the Name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt.</hi> And this was before any diviſions, or ſubdiviſions, were appointed, and they were ſecondarily brought in, for order and better edification, and being parts of the whole receive particular diſtinction from the places where they lived and other particularities. They all retaine the generall forme and eſſentiall difference from heathens; and among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as parts of a ſimilar body, are diſtinguiſhed but by acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall differences.</p>
            <p>And that Promiſe that the <hi>gates of hell ſhall never prevaile againſt the Church</hi> is primarily given to the Church Catholike viſible here on earth, for that in Heaven is not aſſailed by the gates of hell, but onely that on earth. And though it be <hi>applicable to the inviſible onely, yet to thoſe as viſible,</hi> for ſo they are aſſailed, by perſecutions, and hereſies.</p>
            <p>Againe, <hi>He that beleeveth, and is baptized ſhall be ſaved.</hi> This doth primarily belong to the Church Catholike, and that a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church, becauſe capable of Baptiſme, and though it be appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable to every member of any particular Congregation, yet not as being a member thereof, but of the Church Catholike, to which that Promiſe was made: yea, look over all the Promiſes in the New Teſtament, and you ſhall finde them made in generall, without the leaſt reſpect or reference to the particular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations wherein the Beleevers lived. In any ſimilar body, as water, the accidents doe not primarily pertaine to this or that particular drop, and ſecondarily to the whole, but firſt to the whole, and ſecondarily to this or that drop. So the Priviledges of the Church doe not primarily belong to this or that particular Church, and ſecondarily to the generall, but firſt to the generall, and ſecondarily to this particular, being a part of it.</p>
            <p>The maine Priviledges of the Church viſible are, firſt <hi>Federall Holineſſe to the children;</hi> ſecondly, <hi>right to the Ordinances, (quoad nos ſaltem:)</hi> now neither of both theſe betide any man primarily as a member of a particular Congregation, but as a member of the Church Catholike.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Federall</hi> or <hi>Covenant Holineſſe,</hi> whereby the children are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> betideth no mans children, becauſe the parents are of this or that particular Congregation, but becauſe of the Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:123237:16"/>
and this appeares by divers demonſtrations. I will give you but one. <hi>That which ſhould have been, though the particular relation had never been, and which continueth when the particular relation ceaſeth, that is not a proper Priviledge of that relation, but ſuch is federall Holineſſe,</hi> in regard of relation to any particular Church. Suppoſe thoſe baptized by <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> or by Chriſts Diſciples before there was any particular diſtinction, ſhould have any children, or the <hi>Eunuch</hi> (if he were an Eunuch by office on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not in body) baptized by <hi>Philip,</hi> and went immediately home into his own country, ſhould not their children be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>? Suppoſe a Church diſſolved by warre, the Miniſter and people ſlaine, and ſome women left with childe ſhould be carryed away captive, ſhould not thoſe children be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe the particular relation is extinct? Doe not thoſe women remaine members of the Church? Are they to be counted <hi>without,</hi> in the Apoſtles ſence?</p>
            <p>Secondly, for <hi>Ordinances,</hi> either of <hi>Worſhip,</hi> or <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> they are both Priviledges of the Church Catholike, primarily. For Worſhip, a man or a childe hath right to Baptiſme as a member of the Church Catholike, and not of the particular Congregation, for they had right before Congregations were diſtinguiſhed, as in <hi>John Baptiſts,</hi> and Chriſts time, and the Eunuchs caſe, and have right after that relation ceaſeth as children born in captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as in the former inſtances, ſuch children being holy, are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Baptiſme. <hi>Infantes baptizandi ſunt, non ut ſancti ſint, ſed quia ſancti ſunt. Whitak,</hi> And therefore no queſtion but any Miniſter might baptize thoſe children, if he could come by them.</p>
            <p>And for hearing the Word of God, let a Chriſtian dwell where he will, and have opportunity to heare the Word where he can, he hath right to it, and doth heare it, not as a heathen that is <hi>without,</hi> but as his rightfull portion. And even in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregationall Churches, the brethren in one Congregation com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate at the Lords Table in other Congregations, as occaſion is offered. And no queſtion but any Chriſtian may joyne in prayer, and ſay, <hi>Our Father,</hi> &amp;c. with any Chriſtians in the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt parts of the world.</p>
            <p>And for the Ordinances of Diſcipline, every one as a member of the Church Catholike is bound to ſubmit thereunto, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:123237:17"/>
every officer of the Church Catholike viſible hath right to &amp; pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the Ordinances of Diſcipline, <hi>in actu primo,</hi> every where, as ſhall be ſhewed more afterward. And certainly the Church Catholike, even in their repreſentative miniſteriall body, have more extenſive authoritative power then particular Claſſes or Congregations, though haply not more intenſive.</p>
            <p>Neither can it be imagined, that all the other Priviledges ſhould belong firſt to the Church Catholike, and ſo deſcend to particulars, and this of Diſcipline ſhould belong firſt to the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular congregation, and ſo aſcend to the Catholike: that ſome ſhould go in a <hi>geneticall</hi> method (as it were) and others in an <hi>analyticall.</hi> Suppoſe an Apoſtle ſhould have preached in a citie, and converted at firſt but two or three, or converted a company of women, as it was <hi>Pauls</hi> lot to preach to a company of women, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.13. So that they could not be brought in to an organi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call congregation, could it be conceived that they, though bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, were ſtill <hi>without?</hi> and were not their children <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>? And if any of them ſhould miſcarry in their judgements, or practiſes, had <hi>Paul</hi> nothing to doe to cenſure them, becauſe they were not in a <hi>Church way</hi> (as ſome terme it) or in a particular Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though they were in the Church Catholike viſible? If they were lyable to cenſure, or capable thereof, not being in a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar congregation, but the Church Catholike only; then Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline belongs to the Church Catholike, and that primarily. <hi>The Keyes of Diſcipline were first given to the Church Catholike, becauſe firſt given to the Apoſtles, who were generall Paſtours, and therefore the Keyes are Catholike.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo cenſures paſt in one Congregation reach the whole Church Catholike viſible, as ſhall be ſhewed more afterward. <hi>That which belongeth to all and every part of a ſimilar body, as parts of that body, that primarily belongeth to the whole: but ſo doth Diſcipline. Therefore,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>3</label> Thirdly, <hi>Chriſts Offices</hi> are firſt intended for, and executed on the Church Catholike here below. He is <hi>King, Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,</hi> primarily in reſpect of the whole, and but ſecondarily in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of a particular congregation or member. Gods aime in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption was to redeeme the whole firſtly, and ſecondarily par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. <hi>God ſo loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:123237:17"/>
And ſo is the application of that redemption by Chriſt. As a Prieſt he reconcileth, cleanſeth and intercedeth for all of the elect, and proffers it to the whole Church Catholike viſible. As a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet he teacheth all. As a King he ruleth all primarily, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars ſecondarily. As an earthly King is indeed King of <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> &amp;c. but not primarily, but ſecondarily as they are members of his kingdome. And the naturall head is indeed head to the little finger and little toe, but not primarily, but as they are parts of the whole body, whereof it is head: ſo is Chriſt a myſticall King and head firſt of the whole, and ſecondarily of the particular parts contained in and under the whole. Yea Chriſt may be King, Prieſt, and Prophet to a <hi>particular convert,</hi> brought in, and nouriſhed by the word of God preached in a viſible congregation, <hi>before he be admitted a member</hi> of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, or any other by publike conſent, remaining in no Church but the Church Catholike viſible, and haply ſcarce being a compleat member of that, being as yet not baptized.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>the ſignes that difference a true Church from a falſe,</hi> do <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>4</label> not primarily belong to a particular congregation, but to the Church Catholike viſible, viz <hi>profeſſion of the true faith; the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the true ordinances of God, the Word and Sacraments,</hi> for therein all the whole Church agree, and is thereby diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from thoſe that are <hi>without,</hi> not from thoſe that are <hi>within.</hi> This is no note to know this or that particular Church by, from another, for it is common to the univerſall Church, it diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth not among themſelves, but from the generall common op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite, the heathen, or the groſſe heretick. A man being lead into a vault where were the ſculls of many dead men, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that <hi>Alexanders</hi> ſcull was there, deſired his guide to ſhew him that, his guide told him it was that ſcull with the hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low eye holes, and with the griſtly noſe, and with futures croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the brain pann, and when the man replyed that they had all ſo, yea ſaith his guide, there is no difference between Kings and other mens ſculls, when they are dead. So if any man ſhould ask you or me which is the Church of <hi>Ipſwich, Dedham</hi> or <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi> it were a folly to ſay it is the Church where the word of God is preached, and ſacraments adminiſtred, and that profeſſe Ieſus Chriſt to be crucifyed, dead and buryed, riſen again, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:123237:18"/>
aſcended into Heaven, for ſo do all the Church Catholike, but I muſt give ſome other notes to diſtinguiſh any of them, for theſe are <hi>not diſtinctive, becauſe common.</hi> Therefore the ſignes of the true Church belong primarily to the whole, ſecondarily to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular parts thereof, and are therfore <hi>not diſtinctive to the parts.</hi> That which is <hi>primary</hi> to any thing <hi>is diſtinctive</hi> to that thing, but that which is <hi>ſecondary</hi> and common is <hi>not diſtinctive</hi> from other particulars of the like kind.</p>
            <p>Fiftly <hi>all the members of particular Churches are members of the Church, Catholike, yea that relation belongs firſt to them. If they be born</hi> within the pale of the Church, they have federall holines, and are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not becauſe members of this or that congregation, but becauſe born of parents within the generall covenant exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, and ſo within the Church Catholike. <hi>If they be converted</hi> from heathens, they are not firſt converted into this or that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church, but converted firſt into the Church Catholike, and then ſecondarily admitted members of this or that particular congregation. A man may dwell in one City, and heare the word of God by accident in another city, and thereby be converted, but he is not converted to be a member of the Church, where he was converted but into the Church Catholike. So that <hi>particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations are made up of members of the Church Catholike,</hi> &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt properly are ſaid to be <hi>Ortae,</hi> for ſuch a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>vert may joine himſelfe after his converſion, to what congregation he pleaſeth to inhabit among. If a man come into a pariſh that is a heathen, he is not a member of that particular Church, becauſe not a member of the Church Catholike, but if he be a Chriſtian, then is he a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of that particular congregation where he reſideth, or fit ſo to be, and ought not to be denyed admiſſion or communion, though he had never bin member of any other. The particular compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in <hi>London</hi> are made up only of free men, that are joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in ſome particular body or ſociety, belonging to ſuch or ſuch a hall, now the firſt notion that comes upon any of theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or companies, is that they are freemen of <hi>London,</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condarily that they are diſtinct from other free men, by being of this or that particular ſociety, belonging to ſuch a hall. So it is for all Churches, <hi>Firſt,</hi> all the members are conceived to be <hi>free of the Church Catholike,</hi> and <hi>ſecondarily, diſtinct by their ſocieties,</hi> in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:123237:18"/>
this or that particular aſſembly. And though haply this ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude holdeth not in every thing, as the not removing from one company to another, and being received in there, becauſe he is a freeman, yet is it free for any Chriſtian to change his particular relation from one congregation to another, becauſe he is a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and takes not up his firſt freedome into a particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation or company, but in to the Catholik? They are made members of the whole, by converſion to the faith, and initiated by the ſacrament of baptiſme externally, but are <hi>ſecondarily</hi> made members of a particular congregation, by cohabitation, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociation. Suppoſe a man had abundance of ſheep as <hi>Abraham, Iſaack, Jacob,</hi> and <hi>Job,</hi> who had 14000. and theſe ſheep had all one brand of the owners upon them, and theſe ſheep were divided into ſeverall flocks, under ſeverall ſhepheards, in ſeverall ſheep-walks, of the ſame owners, according to his appointment, the primary conſideration of any of theſe ſheep or flocks, is not that they are under ſuch a keeper, in ſuch a ſheep walk, but the firſt conſideration of them is that they are ſuch a mans ſheep, either bought or bred &amp;c. bearing his brand, and fed by his ſervants, on his ground, and then the more particular and ſecondary conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and notion is that they are under ſuch a particular ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard in ſuch a particular walke. And ſo the firſt conſideration of any part of Gods flock, whether perſon or Congregation is, that they are Gods people, borne or converted to him, fed and nouriſhed by his Ordinances, and Miniſters, and then the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ſecondary notion is, that they are fed by ſuch a Paſtour, in ſuch a place.</p>
            <p>It is an uſuall ſimilitude on all hands to compare the Church to the Sea or Ocean, which though it be one, yet as it waſheth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this, or that countrey, receiveth the name and diſtinction of the Germane, Spaniſh, Iriſh, Brittiſh Seas. And ſo when it puts in at any creeke, becauſe it is continuous with the Sea we call it the Sea. And we ſay the ſea comes up at <hi>Harwich, Ipſwich, Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, Colcheſter,</hi> now it were an abſurd thing for any man to think that the particular ſeas were the prime ſeas, and the maine is <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ortum.</hi> Or becauſe the name ſea is indulged to this or that arme or creeke, that therefore that ſhould either monopolize the name Sea, that there ſhould be no ſea but ſuch creekes, or that any
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:123237:19"/>
ſuch creekes ſhould arrogate the name and priviledges of the ſea firſt to themſelves, and leave them but ſecondarily to the maine. So it is for particular Congregations, which have the name and Priviledges of the Church indulged to them at ſecond, or third hand, (becauſe they are members and ſimilar parts of the whole) to uſurp and challenge the name and Priviledges given by God to the Church Catholike, primarily to themſelves, and leave them ſecondarily to the Church Catholike.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>6</label> Sixthly, <hi>the Miniſters are primarily Miniſters of the Church Catholike;</hi> ſecondarily, of this or that particular flock or congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation: and therefore the Catholike is the prime Church. And this appeares by this demonſtration. <hi>That Church to the which the donation of the Miniſtry was firſt made, is the firſt ſubject thereof, but that was the Church Catholike, therefore.</hi> For proofe hereof ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28, 29. <hi>God hath ſet ſome in the Church firſt Apoſtles, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condarily Prophets, thirdly Teachers.</hi> Now this Church was the Church Catholike, and not any particular congregation, for it is the Church to which the Lord gave <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> Note alſo from hence, that <hi>the ſame Church to which God gave Apoſtles, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, to the ſame he gave Teachers alſo.</hi> Biſhop, and Paſtour may ſeeme to be in reſpect to the particular relation to ſome particular place, wherein by the politie of the Church a particular Miniſter is ſet, but Presbyter, Miniſter, and Teacher, more generall, exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the whole Church Catholike. <hi>Paul</hi> an Apoſtle cals him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <hi>a Teacher and Preacher,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Peter</hi> alſo and <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtles call themſelves Presbyters, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1. 2 <hi>Ep. Joh.</hi> 1.3 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. we finde alſo that Miniſters are in Scripture ſpoken of under a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall notion. They are called <hi>Miniſters of the Word, Luke</hi> 1.2. and <hi>Miniſters of God,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.4. And <hi>Miniſters of Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. And <hi>Ministers of the New Testament,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. And <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Gospell,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ</hi> 3.2. And <hi>Miniſters of the Lord, Eph.</hi> 6.21. where the Miniſteriall Office is noted by the reference thereof to the Author that imployeth them, and the ſubject about which they are imployed, and not by the Object to whom they preached, <hi>They are not called Miniſters of the people, but their Teachers, Rulers, Paſtours, Overſeers,</hi> or <hi>Miniſters for them, Col.</hi> 1.7.</p>
            <p>And if a Miniſter of this or that Congregation were not a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:123237:19"/>
Miniſter of the Church Catholike viſible, <hi>then he were no Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter out of his own Congregation, and therefore could not preach, or administer any Sacrament, as a Miniſter, out of his own Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Yea, if any members of another Congregation ſhould come and heare a Miniſter in his owne Congregation, he could not preach to them, nor they heare him as a Miniſter, but only as a gifted brother. And though he may pray and beſeech his owne flock as an Ambaſſadour of Chriſt to be reconciled unto God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. yet he cannot ſay ſo to any other, except he be an Ambaſſadour in office unto others alſo; and if he be a Miniſter to one member beſides his own Congregation, then is he ſo indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely to all, by the ſame reaſon. But if he deliver the Word as a Miniſter to his own Congregation only, then the ſame Word which is delivered at the ſame time by the ſame man is delivered by vertue of Miniſteriall Office to ſome, and to others <hi>ex officio charitatis generali,</hi> onely as a gifted brother. And if this be granted, which is abſurd, yet a greater abſurdity will follow, <hi>viz.</hi> that if he adminiſter the Lords Supper to any members of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Congregation, he muſt doe that alſo as a gifted brother, and as a private perſon, which yet all men hold hath nothing to doe to adminiſter the Scales of the Covenant. And yet this commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of members of other Congregations is frequent among our brethren for Congregationall Churches. Neither can this be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered that it is done by vertue of conſociation of Churches, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the conſociation of Churches and their members make alſo a conſociation of offices and officers, and ſo every Miniſter be a generall officer, and a Miniſter of the Church Catholike, as well as the particular members be members of the Church Catholike. And if a Miniſter of one Congregation be a generall officer, and can adminiſter the Seales of the Covenant, Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper, to ſtrangers in his own congregation in his owne meeting-houſe, then any where elſe in any other meeting houſe, for no man will ſay his miniſteriall office is circumſcribed by, or tyed unto the limits and fabrick of his own meeting houſe, or any eſpeciall influence or authority afforded him in the execution of his miniſteriall function by the preſence of his owne congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. He whoſe office is limited within, and ſtands wholly in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation unto a particular place, is out of office when he is out of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:123237:20"/>
that place, as a Major of a Corporation, and Conſtable of a Pariſh, but it is not ſo with a Miniſter, he is no private man, as ſoon as he is out of his meeting houſe, or the limits of his congregation, and though he indeed be peculiarly their Paſtour or Biſhop, one that hath the overſight of them in the Lord in a more immediate eſpeciall manner, yet this extends to all times, and places, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he or they ſhall come by occaſion, though never ſo farre from their dwellings, but ſo is not a Major or Conſtable. And beſides that particular office he is an officer, a Miniſter in generall to all others, and may execute his office to them as God giveth him occaſion, but ſo cannot a Major or Conſtable, becauſe they are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly particular officers. Suppoſe a Miniſters flock by mortality, captivity, or the ſword, ſhould be diſſolved, extinct, and faile, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he ceaſeth to be their Paſtour, becauſe the correlative faileth, but he ceaſeth not to be a Miniſter of the Goſpell. A King or Major haply ceaſe to be ſo any longer, if his Kingdome, or Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſhould ſinke, becauſe there is no Catholike Kingdome, or Townſhip whereof they were officers, but the office of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ceaſeth not, becauſe he was an officer of the Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, which correlate ſinketh not. And being an officer of the Church Catholike, he hath thereby <hi>actum primum</hi> to adminiſter all the Ordinances of Chriſt, which a ſingle officer may or can doe in any place, only wanteth <hi>actum ſecundum, vel exercitum, pro hic &amp; nunc</hi> which is appointed by the politie of the Church, for order. For though their office be generall, as Miniſters of the Goſpell, yet they take particular diviſions, and parcels of the Church to feed, and ſtretch not themſelves within one anothers line, without a call, by permiſſion or intreaty.</p>
            <p>And that a Miniſter is a Miniſter of the Church Catholike viſible appeares by this argument. <hi>He that can miniſterially</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>eject</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>admit</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <hi>a member</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>out of</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>into</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <hi>the Church Catholike viſible, is a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister, and Officer of the Church Catholike viſible. But every Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister by</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Excommunication</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Baptiſme</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>ejecteth</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>admitteth</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <hi>members</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>out of</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>into</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <hi>the Church Catholike viſible, Therefore, &amp;c.</hi> This argument I finde more fully laid downe by <hi>Apollonius,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Paſtor ut Paſtor exercet multos actus miniſteriales non tantum erga Eccleſiam ſuam particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larem
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:123237:20"/>
cujus ordinario Miniſterio eſt affixus, ſed etiam erga Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias alias Particulares, &amp; Provinciales, &amp; Nationales, imò &amp; er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga Eccleſiam <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſalem: Nam per Baptiſmum membra in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam univerſalem admittit. Per Excommunicationem membra non tantum ex ſua particulari ſed etiam Provinciali, Nationali, &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſali Eccleſia ejicit. Matth. <hi>18.18, 19.</hi> Ex officio pastorali preces Deo offert pro omnibus aliis Eccleſiis laborantibus: Verbum Dei in alia Eccleſia particulari praedicare poteſt, non tantum virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te &amp; ratione donorum, ſed cum paſtorali authoritate, ita ut verbo ſuo liget &amp; ſolvat peccatores, remittat &amp; retineat peccata, &amp; ut le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatus miſſus à Deo obſecret homines ut reconcilientur Deo. Gul. Apollon. conſideratio quarundam, &amp;c." pag. <hi>86.</hi>
               </q> Of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation I ſpake before, proving that it ejecteth a man out of the whole Church Catholike viſible: which though it be paſſed with the knowledge and conſent of the Congregation, (as alſo is Baptiſme) yet it is an act of the Presbyters. But becauſe it is an act of many <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 2.6.</note>, I will therefore inſiſt more large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and particularly upon Baptiſme, which is the act of a ſingle Paſtour or Miniſter. That by Baptiſme we are admitted into the Church, I thinke is without doubt, for if perſons baptized be not members of a viſible Church, <hi>then the Seale of the Covenant, yea the initiall Seale thereof, is adminiſtred to thoſe that are and remain out of the Church,</hi> which were abſurd to ſay. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Ball</hi> in his <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme</hi> hath this paſſage. <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Baptiſme is a Sacrament of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafting into Chriſt, Communion with him, and <hi>entrance into the Church,</hi> for which he citeth <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.38. And afterward explaines himſelfe. It doth, ſaith he, ſolemnely ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie and ſeale their engrafting into Chriſt, and <hi>confirme that they are acknowledged members of the Church,</hi> and entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, though it doth not make us Chriſtian ſoules."</q> And that we are thereby admitted members, not of a particular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, but the Church Catholike appeares, becauſe we are <hi>bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed into one body,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. And this appeares further, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he that is baptized in one Congregation, is baptized all over the world, and is not to be rebaptized, but is taken as a member where-ever he becomes. Now that <hi>baptizing</hi> is an <hi>act of office</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares <hi>John</hi> 1.33. <hi>He that ſent me to baptize: And goe teach all nations, and baptize them,</hi> was the ſubſtance of the Apoſtles Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:123237:21"/>
And though <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17. ſaith, <hi>Chriſt ſent me not to baptize, but to preach the Gospell,</hi> yet that is meant <hi>not princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally,</hi> for he was ſent alſo to baptize, elſe he might not have done it. And that by vertue of this office, we are <hi>baptized into the Church Catholike,</hi> appeares, becauſe <hi>John Baptiſt, baptized all Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, Judea, and the Region round about Jordan: And the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Chriſt made and baptized more Diſciples then John,</hi> and that <hi>without relation to any particular Congregations,</hi> which had it been neceſſary they could have combined them into. So <hi>Peter</hi> cauſed <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his friends to be baptized, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.48. but no mention is made of any Congregation into which they were baptized. And <hi>Philip</hi> baptized the <hi>Eunuch</hi> not into any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Congregation. And the Apoſtles carryed about one with them, whom they called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a Miniſter, Acts</hi> 13.5. who was no Apoſtle, and he baptized for them. So <hi>Tychicus, Col.</hi> 4.7. is called a <hi>beloved brother,</hi> and <hi>faithfull Miniſter,</hi> and <hi>fellow-ſervant in the Lord,</hi> yet he was none of their Miniſter: and <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.21. he hath the ſame ſtile given him againe, certainly he could not be a peculiar Miniſter to both thoſe diſtant Churches, and I ſuppoſe he was of neither. <hi>Appollos baptized at Corinth,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.4. and yet was no Apoſtle, but as <hi>a Miniſter, and ſteward of the Myſteries of God, as well as they,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. Hence is this diſtinction of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> in his <hi>Animadverſions</hi> on <hi>Bellaerm. cap.</hi> 7. <hi>nota</hi> 7. <hi>Alia eſt electio ſive vocatio communis, qua vir bonus, pius, doctus, aptus, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſòlutè eligitur ad miniſterium verbi, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: Alia particularis ſive ſingularis quâ ad ministerium ſingulariter huic vel illi Eccleſiae praeficiendus eligitur,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>And the truth is, the Scripture alwayes calling the Beleevers in one Citie one Church; even Jeruſalem though there were many thouſands, yea, <hi>myriads,</hi> that is, many times ten thouſands, of beleeving Jewes therein, as <hi>James</hi> tels <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 21.20. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (which were all probably of Jeruſalem, as appeares, firſt becauſe they were not ſuch as could <hi>beare any witneſſe againſt Paul</hi> but by hear-ſay: <hi>they are informed of thee:</hi> but the Jewes amongſt the Gentiles diſperſt having ſeen and heard <hi>Paul,</hi> could have teſtified of their own knowledge, <hi>and would not be blinded with Pauls preſent conformity.</hi> And ſecondly, becauſe they only of Jeruſalem could receive ſatisfaction by <hi>Pauls</hi> conformity to the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:123237:21"/>
Law, at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> at that time, and not the others) And alſo the Holy Ghoſt calling the Elders in thoſe Cities, the Elders of the Church, in <hi>communi,</hi> it leaveth it uncertaine to me, whether the ſeverall Elders were fixed over particular congregations, or taught and ruled <hi>in communi,</hi> as the Miniſters do now in <hi>Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> and <hi>Strasburgh,</hi> and other places, yet becauſe it maketh moſt for edification, and order, to have them fixed, I ſhall thinke they were, untill the contrary ſhall be proved. And I verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve <hi>they ruled in communi,</hi> though haply they did not teach ſo.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, <hi>that Church to which every Chriſtian bears firſt relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and which relation continueth laſt, and cannot be broken by him without ſin, is the firſt Church: but ſuch is the Church Catholike viſible, therfore.</hi> Them nor appeares, becauſe none can be admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a particular congregation except he be judged firſt of the Church Catholike: ſo againe though he change his habitation never ſo often, and beare relation to never ſo many particular congregations, one after another, yet in all thoſe the generall relation holdeth ſtill, he is a baptized viſible member of the Church Catholike, and therfore to be received where ever he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh into any particular congregation. Yea in the <hi>Interim</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween his breaking off from one congregation and placing in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother congregation, he retaines the generall relation, and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and is not a heathen or infidell, he is not one <hi>without</hi> in the Apoſtles phraſe. Yea ſuppoſe a man ſhould be a Traveller, Merchant or Factour, and ſetled in no particular congregation, yet being a Chriſtian he is a member of the Church Catholike: yea and if he broach any errours, or live inordinately, he ſhall be accountable to the Church wherein he for the preſent reſides, or ſuch crimes are committed, and be lyable to their cenſure, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a member of the Church Catholike: which appeares in that the <hi>Church of Epheſus is commended Rev.</hi> 1.2.<note place="margin">☜</note> 
               <hi>for trying ſtrangers that came among them, under the notion of Apoſtles. And finding them lyars did not ſuffer them;</hi> now prohibition is a cenſure. They are not to be left to the Magiſtrate only, but to the Church tryall, for thoſe crimes come not alwayes under the cognizance of the civill Magiſtrates, and if they do, he may be a heathen and will not regard an haeretick, nor can judge of him. And if every
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:123237:22"/>
kingdome will try murder, or treaſon, or any other foule crime committed in the ſame, though by a ſtranger, or alien, becauſe the crimes are againſt their lawes, and ſoveraigne, though their lawes pertain not to the country where the forrainer was borne, and dwelleth, then much more ſhall every Church try thoſe mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church Catholike reſiding among them for their crimes, ſeeing they have all the ſame ſoveraigne head, the ſame lawes, and are all one body.</p>
            <p>Againe it is no ſinne for a man to remove from one congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to another as oft as occaſion requireth, but for a man to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move out of the Church Catholike is a ſinne and apoſtacy. No man is a ſchiſmatick for removing from one congregation to another, but he that ſhall ſeparate himſelfe from all Church com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and ſhall rend himſelfe from the Church Catholike, he is a ſchiſmatick, he is an apoſtate. And therfore your ſeverall ſects though they pretend becauſe of wants or blemiſhes to rend from the Church of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland &amp;c.</hi> Yet not from the Church Catholike by no meanes, becauſe they know that were a ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>8</label> Eighthly, that Church <hi>from which the particular Churches ſpring, and to which they are as an additament and increaſe, that is the prime Church, but that is the Church Catholike,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Act. 2.47.</note> 
               <hi>therfore &amp;c.</hi> The minor appeares, becauſe firſt the whole eſſence of the Church Catholike was in <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> and from them ſpread to his ſeed by their federall right from them, and their actuall taking up that free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and continuance therein. And ſo againe from <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke.</p>
            <p>And for the Church under the Goſpell; that little handfull which Chriſt left, leavened the whole world, and brought them in as an addition unto them. <hi>They were to be witneſſes first in Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, them in Iudea, and then to the ends of the earth. For the Law ſhall go forth of Zion and the word of God from Jeruſalem. Iſa.</hi> 2.3. It was with the Church then as was ſaid of the river of <hi>Eden Gen.</hi> 2.10. <hi>A river went out of Eden to water the garden, and from thence it was parted and became into</hi> 4. <hi>heads:</hi> ſo the water of life flowed from <hi>Zion</hi> into the 4. quarters of all the world. So that as there is no Sea but hath influence, and continuity with the maine Sea, and receives name from thence: ſo no particular Church but hath his firſt riſe, and ſpirituall miniſteriall influence from the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:123237:22"/>
Church Catholike, and received the Goſpell and priviledges of it from thence. God cals no Evangelicall Churches by inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but by the miniſtry of thoſe that are members of the Church Catholike, or ſome part thereof, and therfore God would not have <hi>Cornelius</hi> inſtructed by an Angell, though he could have done it, but by <hi>Peter,</hi> a member of the Church Evangelicall. So that the Church is as the Sea, and particular Churches as ſo many creeks, or armes, and rivers, not running into the ſea, but <hi>run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from</hi> the ſea, and receiving a tincture and ſeaſon of her wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. The Church Catholike is as the <hi>tree,</hi> Chriſt as the <hi>root,</hi> and particular Churches as <hi>branches.</hi> She is the <hi>mother</hi> and they as <hi>daughters</hi> born of her, and receiving from her miniſterially both nature, name and priviledges. <hi>Paul</hi> indeed was called <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily</hi> from Heaven by <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, the head of the Church (and not by an Angell) that he might be, as ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, a type of the ſecond call of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> who (as ſome bold) ſhall be ſo called as he was, <hi>by the appearing of the ſigne of the ſon of man,</hi> and therfore that Church is ſaid to <hi>come downe from God out of Heaven, Rev.</hi> 21.2, 10. And the ground for this type they take from 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.16. <hi>For this cauſe I obtained mercy that in me firſt Ieſus Chriſt might ſhew forth all long ſufferance for a patterne, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to them which ſhould or ſhall hereafter beleeve on him:</hi> but theſe things are myſteries, and I dare not be too confident in them, yet ſhould they come to paſſe, they infringe not the preſent truth, becauſe their converſion ſhall come from the <hi>head, root,</hi> and <hi>fountaine</hi> it ſelfe of the Church, as <hi>Abrahams</hi> call was; and no queſtion but Chriſt did convert ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in the dayes of his fleſh when he was actually and viſibly a member of the Church here below. And if any be converted by ſecret <hi>revelation,</hi> or <hi>inspiration,</hi> and neither converted, nor fed by any externall ordinances, nor joyned to any viſible Church, as infants of heathens, or any of the Philoſophers as <hi>Plato</hi> (if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly they may be ſuch) theſe are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and not within the compaſſe of the generall rule for the viſible Church, and ſo not of the queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> If it be asked, what it is that is ſufficient to make a man a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church Catholike viſible? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer, Beliefe of the maine points of the Chriſtian faith, &amp; profeſſed ſubjection there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:123237:23"/>
And this is as much as the Apoſtles required, as in the caſe of the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> and <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> and if it were ſufficient then, it is ſufficient ſtill: for thoſe were the pureſt Churches. <hi>So many as gladly received the Word were baptized, Acts</hi> 2.41. And yet this is no more then may be found in an hypocrite, for the ſtony ground received the Word with joy. And we have no other rule to goe by in gathering Churches, or receiving mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers into a Church, then they had then, neither may we preſume to make any other to our ſelves. <hi>Sic omnes ferè Reformati Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logi celebres materiam viſibilis Eccleſia aſſerunt eſſe homines externè vocatos fidem Chriſti profitentes: nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> definiunt caetum hominum vocatione externa ſeu praedicatione Verbi &amp; Sacramentorum commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicatione evocatorum ad cultum Dei &amp; ſocietatem Eccleſiaſticam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſe celebrandam. Apolon. pag.</hi> 8. <hi>Vide etiam utrum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Trelcatium in locis communibus, Loc. de Eccleſia &amp; Profeſſores Leidenſes, Disp.</hi> 40. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. Neither is it requiſite that they ſhould be truly godly, to make them members of a viſible Church, for then no man could tell whoſe child were to be baptized, or who are members of a Church, or when he is in a true Church. And if the living mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> were the only, or eſſentiall members of a viſible Church, then none are true eſſentiall members of the Church viſible but they, and then a truly godly Miniſter is a more eſſentiall Miniſter then another, and the Ordinances adminiſtred by him are more eſſentially adminiſtred then by another, and the vertue of the Ordinance ſhould depend, not on Chriſts Inſtitution, but the worthineſſe of the perſon adminiſtring. And haply af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter twenty or thirty yeares living under a Miniſter that ſeemed religious, that Miniſter by falling away proves himſelfe not to be truly godly, and ſo all thoſe Ordinances were null, being admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred by one that was not only no Miniſter, but no true member of the Church. I conclude this anſwer with that ſaying in <hi>Ameſ.</hi> in his <hi>Bellar. enervat. Falſum eſt internas virtutes requiri à nobis ut aliquis ſit in Eccleſia quoad viſibilem ejus ſtatum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> The Church Catholike is <hi>Integrum,</hi> and the particular Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are <hi>membra,</hi> and therefore neither of them can be <hi>Prima,</hi> or <hi>Orta,</hi> in reference of one to another, becauſe being <hi>Relata,</hi> they are <hi>ſimul naturâ,</hi> and both <hi>Integrum &amp; membra</hi> are both of them <hi>Orta argumenta. Vide Rami Dialecticam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:123237:23"/>Indeed we finde in Logick that both <hi>Genus</hi> and <hi>Species,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> 
               <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grum &amp; membra,</hi> are <hi>Orta Argumenta,</hi> and that it is not meant in reference one to another, but to thoſe arguments which are called <hi>Prima,</hi> as <hi>Cauſe, Effect, Subject, Adjunct,</hi> and <hi>Contraries.</hi> And it would be a Logicall diſpute, not Theologicall, to define whether <hi>Integrum</hi> or <hi>membra</hi> have the primary conſideration, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they are <hi>Relata, Quorum alterum constat è mutuâ alterius af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectione. Ergo dicuntur ſimul eſſe naturâ:</hi> For <hi>Totum eſt quod ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet partes, Pars eſt quae continetur à toto.</hi> So that a thing cannot be ſaid to be a whole but in reference to the parts, nor can any thing be ſaid to be a part but in reference to the whole, for though it may have a being before the whole, yet it is not a part of the whole untill the whole be.</p>
            <p>Yet for the clearing of this Objection we muſt conſider that <hi>Integrum &amp; membra</hi> admit of divers kinds, and conſiderations, and though in a conſtant permanent or continuous body, whoſe particular individuall parts riſe and fall together with the whole, ſo that it cannot conſiſt but of ſo many eſſentiall individuall parts whereof it is conſtituted, there the whole and the parts whereof it is conſtituted as they ſtand in relation unto one another muſt be <hi>ſimul naturâ,</hi> yet the Church Catholike being, as I may ſay, a kinde of <hi>diſcreet, ſucceſſive, indefinite</hi> body, alwayes <hi>tranſient</hi> and in <hi>flux,</hi> ſome members being alwayes in their adding and ſome alwayes in taking away, ſo that even in reſpect of the particular parts it is not one houre every way the ſame it was the laſt, I ſay, that in reference to the members that are to be added, the whole muſt needs be accounted firſt, becauſe it hath a being before the addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and after the ſubſtraction, and the members muſt needs be firſt added to the whole before they can beare the relation of parts unto it. And herein it is like a Corporation, whoſe firſt members whereof it is conſtituted are <hi>ſimul naturâ</hi> with the whole, yet all the members that are added ſucceſſively finde it a Corporation before their addition, and ſo are not <hi>ſimul naturâ</hi> with the whole.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> The Church Catholike is made up of the particular Churches,and therefore it is <hi>Orta,</hi> and they are <hi>Prima?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> To let paſſe Logicall diſputes,conſider we the univerſall and particular Churches in a theologicall notion, and we ſhall
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:123237:24"/>
find (as hath been already proved) that the particular Churches or congregations do riſe out of the Church Catholike, and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. For the members of a particular congregation are firſt members of the Church Catholike, and admitted thereinto, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they come to be capable of being members of a particular Congregation: for no Congregation takes a heathen in firſt, and makes him a member, and then a Chriſtian, but he is firſt made a Chriſtian, and then made a member. Yea, I conceive that there may be many belonging to the Church Catholike, that belong to no particular Congregation, whoſe converſion hath been by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentall providence, as by reading, or diſcourſe, or haply hearing a diſputation, or Sermon, and yet their habitation, or impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſlavery, baniſhment, travell, or other occaſions may not ſuffer them to joyne themſelves to any particular Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and yet are viſible Chriſtians yeelding profeſſed ſubjection to the Goſpell in their lives and converſations. And are, by being of the Church Catholike, fit to be members of any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, but are actually none. Suppoſe a man by tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planting into <hi>America,</hi> ſuffering ſhipwrack, ſhould ſwimme to ſome unknowne land, and there live among the natives, is that man <hi>without?</hi> or if he ſhould convert a native to the faith in Chriſt, is he <hi>without?</hi> is he not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>? Of what Congregation was the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> that was baptized by <hi>Philip?</hi> and yet we doubt not to ſay, he was a Chriſtian, and one of the Church members, but it muſt be the Church Catholike.</p>
            <p>So that we ſee the Church Catholike conſiſteth not of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Congregations only, but particular members, that may not haply be drawne into congregations. As not only all Cities, Towns, and Pariſhes in a Kingdome belong to that Kingdome, but all particular Perſons living under, and by the ſame lawes, though haply there ſhould be ſome that live not in any townſhip or village, but in ſome Iſland, forreſt, or in ſhips, as the manner is of many families in the Netherlands, or as I have heard of ſome houſe that ſtands ſo that no Pariſh in their Perambulation did over fetch it in.</p>
            <p>And if we muſt account the particular Churches to be <hi>primae,</hi> becauſe the Church Catholike is made up of them, then we muſt account particular families to be the prime Churches, becauſe the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:123237:24"/>
Congregations are made up of them, and they are called Churches in the Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.19. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Philem.</hi> 2. And we know God had his Church in families in the Patriarchs times before it was either Nationall or Congregationall.</p>
            <p>But it is plaine that particular Congregations are made up of a certain number or parcell of the members of the Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, and not contrary. And ſo were the Churches in fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies alſo.</p>
            <p>Now then, ſeeing it is evident by the former Scriptures, and Arguments, that there is a Church Catholike viſible: And ſeeing that the Names, Nature, and Priviledges of the Church, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and Ordinances of God, the Offices of Chriſt, and Signes of the true Church, the Members of the Church, and Miniſtry of the Word, belong firſt to the Church Catholike viſible, and that every particular Chriſtian beare firſt and laſt relation thereunto, which relation cannot be broken off by any removall, or without ſinne, and that particular Churches ſpring out of the Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, I therefore conclude according to the light God hath given me, That the Church Catholike viſible is <hi>Prima,</hi> and the particular Churches are <hi>Ortae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From this <hi>Theſis</hi> give me leave to propound to your further conſideration theſe Corollaries or Concluſions,</p>
            <p>Concerning
<list>
                  <item>Churches
<list>
                        <item>Catholike.</item>
                        <item>Particular.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>Perſons
<list>
                        <item>Publike, <hi>viz.</hi> the Officers.</item>
                        <item>Private, <hi>viz.</hi> the members.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <list>
               <head>Concerning the Church in generall.</head>
               <item n="1">1. That there is a Church Catholike.</item>
               <item n="2">2. That the Church Catholike is but one.</item>
               <item n="3">3. That the Church Catholike is viſible.</item>
               <item n="4">4. That though the Church Catholike be alwayes tranſient and in flux by the addition and ſubtraction of the members there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, yet it ſhall never ceaſe to be viſible.</item>
               <item n="5">5. That if the Church Catholike be contracted into the limits of a particular Congregation, yet that hath the notion of the Church Catholike more properly then of a particular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</item>
               <item n="6">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:123237:25"/>6. That the Church Catholike is mixt of good and bad, as well as particular Congregations are.</item>
               <item n="7">7. That the Church Catholike is Organicall.</item>
               <item n="8">8. That the Keyes of Diſcipline are Catholike as well as of Doctrine.</item>
               <item n="9">9. That the Promiſes, Priviledges, and Ordinances of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Diſcipline belong primarily to the Church Catholike.</item>
               <item n="10">10. That the notes and ſignes of the true Church belong firſt to the Church Catholike viſible, and therefore are diſtinctive to that only.</item>
               <item n="11">11. That the whole Church Catholike is the primary object of Chriſts Offices, and particulars but as parts thereof. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16.</item>
               <item n="12">12. Though Chriſt be the only Supreme head and Ruler of his Church, yet muſt it have immediate ſubordinate rulers over it. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11.</item>
               <item n="13">13. That the Unity of the Church Catholike requireth not a meeting of the whole body together at any time.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Concerning particular Churches.</head>
               <item n="1">1. That particular Churches are made up of the members of the Church Catholike.</item>
               <item n="2">2. That the particular Diviſions of the Church Catholike viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for convenient enjoyment of publike Ordinances have the Name (Church) and the Priviledges thereof by participation (as farre as they are capable) indulged unto them.</item>
               <item n="3">3. That particular Churches muſt be diſtinguiſhed by particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar accidentall limits, and circumſtances, though they be hetero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geneall to the Church.</item>
               <item n="4">4. Many Congregations may be in the ſame community of Diſcipline, and be ruled by their Elders <hi>in communi</hi> by co-ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation though not ſubordination, and ſo be called One Church, Nationall, Provinciall, or Presbyteriall.</item>
               <item n="5">5. That which belongs primarily to the whole Church as <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſimilare,</hi> and to the leaſt part of the whole, as a part thereof, belongs much more to a greater part thereof.</item>
               <item>Or thus, That which belongs to a little part of a ſimilar body, <hi>(quâ talis)</hi> belongs to a greater part much more.</item>
               <item n="6">6. The greater the parts of the Church Catholike be, and the more united by co-ordination, the ſtronger they be, and the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler the Diviſions be, the weaker.</item>
               <item n="7">
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:123237:25"/>7. The Diviſion of the Church Catholike into ſmall parcels to ſtand alone by themſelves without co-ordination is dangerous.</item>
               <item n="8">8. Yet neceſſity in regard of diſtance of place, &amp;c. may cauſe a particular Church to be Independent in regard of actuall exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall conſociation.</item>
               <item n="9">9. The conſtituting a particular Church by an explicite Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant as the eſſentiall forme thereof, implyeth a deniall of all other Churches to be true that are not ſo conſtituted, becauſe they muſt want the eſſentiall forme.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Concerning the publike Officers of the Church.</head>
               <item n="1">1. Every Miniſter is an Officer of the Church Catholike, and that relation is primary to him, yet the particular relation he ſtands in to a particular congregation giveth him by the politic of the Church a more immediate charge to adminiſter the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of God unto them.</item>
               <item n="2">2. Any ſingle Miniſter by vertue of his office hath power mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterially to admit a member into the Church Catholike viſible.</item>
               <item n="3">3. Although the Election of a Miniſter to a particular congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation be an act of liberty in the people, yet his miſſion is from Chriſt primarily, and miniſterially by the Presbytery.</item>
               <item n="4">4. He doth not adminiſter the Ordinances of God in the name of the congregation as their ſervant, but of Chriſt. As a Major in a corporation though choſen by the people, yet executeth his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in the Kings name.</item>
               <item n="5">5. If he adminiſtreth any Ordinances out of his own congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, he doth it not as a gifted brother, but by vertue of his office, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20.</item>
               <item n="6">6. Although the particular flock over which a Miniſter was ſet be diſſolved, yet he ceaſeth not to be a Miniſter, becauſe the Church to which he bare firſt relation is not diſſolved, which is the Catholike.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Concerning private members.</head>
               <item n="1">1. Particular Converts are firſt converted into the Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, and ſecondarily conjoyn'd into particular conſociations.</item>
               <item n="2">2. Every member of a particular Church is a member of the Church Catholike, and that relation doth primarily belong unto him.</item>
               <item n="3">3. Externall profeſſion of the true Faith, and ſubjection to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:123237:26"/>
Gods Ordinances is enough to make a man capable of being a member of a viſible Church, <hi>quoad externam formum.</hi>
               </item>
               <item n="4">4. By Baptiſme members are viſibly and miniſterially admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the Church Catholike viſible.</item>
               <item n="5">5. By Excommunication rightly adminiſtred an offender is caſt out of the Church Catholike viſible as much as out of a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular congregation.</item>
               <item n="6">6. Federall Holineſſe belongs to none primarily, becauſe borne of members of a particular congregation, but of the Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike.</item>
               <item n="7">7. They that are only in the Church Catholike viſible are not <hi>Without,</hi> in the Apoſtles ſenſe.</item>
               <item n="8">8. Children of beleeving parents have right to Baptiſme, though their parents were not members of any particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and are debarred of their due if denyed it.</item>
               <item n="9">9. Every member of the Church Catholike is or ought to be a member of the particular Church wherein he dwells.</item>
               <item n="10">10. The being in the generall Covenant gives right to the Ordinances and not any particular, neither do we find any men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Scripture of any particular explicit Covenant either ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged or uſed at the admiſſion of members into a particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, or at the conſtitution of the ſame.</item>
               <item n="11">11. The Inviſible members of the Church which have inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall communion with Chriſt are alſo viſible members, and have externall communion in externall ordinances.</item>
               <item n="12">12. The departure of a member from a particular congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and removall to another for convenience, or by neceſſity, is no ſinne, but departing from the Church Catholike, and ceaſing to be a member thereof is a ſinne.</item>
            </list>
            <p>I know it is not uſuall to make uſes and application to <hi>Theſes</hi> of this nature, and ſhould I enter thereinto, I might drowne my ſelfe in ſorrow, to bewayle the rents, not in Chriſts ſeame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe coate, but in his body the Church, which Chriſt preferred in ſome regards before his naturall body, for he aſſumed his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall body for their ſakes, and was willing to ſuffer that to be buffeted, ſpit on, whipped, crowned with thornes, crucifyed, peirced, ſlaine, for their ſakes, yea he was willing to be made ſinne, yea a curſe, and to beare his fathers wrath in his humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:123237:26"/>
for his Churches ſake, that they might eſcape and be ſaved.</p>
            <p>The diviſions in the Church are of three ſorts, in judgement, in affection, and in way or practiſe.</p>
            <p>For judgement, firſt come the <hi>Romiſts,</hi> and they rend away the ſecond commandment: then come the <hi>Antiſabbatarians</hi> and they rend away the fourth, though placed in the heart of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calogue, and ſo extraordinarily fenced by God, with a memen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to before it, and ſo many arguments after it: then come the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinomians,</hi> and they pluck away the whole law from us, denying it both punitive, coactive, and directive power, and ſo render it wholy dead and uſeles to Chriſtians: then come the <hi>Socinians,</hi> and they quench the Deity of Chriſt, and the Holy Ghoſt, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny our redemption by the blood of Chriſt, and ſo conſequently would deprive us of the benefit of the New Teſtament: then come the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and they deny and deride our Baptiſme, and render us and our children no better then heathens: then come the <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> and they would pluck up our Church by the roots, and call us Antichriſtian, <hi>Rome, Egypt, Sodome, Babylon,</hi> and ſo conſequently call their owne mother whore, for if they have any converſion they had it in the boſome of our Church. Of whom that of the Pſalmiſt is too true,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.20.</note> Thou fitteſt and ſpeakeſt againſt thy brother, and haſt ſlandered thine own mothers ſonne. Yea there be others of our honoured and beloved brethren, whom I forbeare to name among the former rabble, who though they acknowledge us true Churches, yet deny us to be one Church, and would have us rent into a thouſand pieces and parcels, and theſe to ſtand as ſo many entire, compleat bodies, without any co-ordination, as ſo many Spouſes of Chriſt, as ſo many Queens, appointing their own orders, and officers, as their ſervants to officiate in their names, with liberty to cenſure both officers and members within themſelves by the votes of the whole body; and not to be accountable unto any other Church or Churches as co-ordinate members, except arbitrarily at their pleaſure. Not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring, with us, to reforme our Churches, but to gather Churches out of Churches, by calling our beſt members out of our congregations, and uniting them into ſeverall bodies, by a particular explicit covenant, urged as an ordinance of God, and forme of the Church, and as the only Church way, and way of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:123237:27"/>
God: and ſo having fleeted off for themſelves the creame of our congregations, and tranſplanted all our wheat by it ſelfe into their field, would leave us none but the tares, the lees and dreggs of men. But I forbeare, <hi>Dolor ora repreſſit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others there are, (and I wiſh I could ſay they were others,) who pleade for liberty of judgement, that every one may hold what opinions, and be of what religion, and ſect he pleaſeth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe judgement and conſcience cannot be forced, but muſt be left to God only, and thereby would make <hi>England</hi> another <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterdam</hi> of all ſects and religions; whereas our brethren in <hi>New-England</hi> have baniſhed the Familiſts &amp;c. from amongſt them. Yea and generally men covet new opinions, and count it their glory to differ from others in judgement, and he is no body that hath none but old truths, and ſo men under colour of new light and new truths rake up a multitude of old errours.</p>
            <p>Secondly, our diviſions are in heart and affections: for diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in judgement cauſe alienation of affections, and great thoughts of heart, ſo that if there prove once a claſhing and croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in opinions, though they were never ſo neer allyed, or well acquainted, and familiar, yet then they grow ſtrange, and fall out, and oppoſe, and cenſure each other deeply: then they are ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, or antichriſtian, or enemies to Chriſts kingly office, and hence come ſo many invectives in Pulpit and Preſſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in way: for as mens judgements differ, ſo doe their wayes: Some are for one way of Worſhip, ſome another; ſome for one way of Diſcipline, ſome another; ſome for one way of conſtituting of Churches, ſome another; ſome for gathering of new Churches out of the old, and yet let the old ones ſtand as mock-churches, when they have gleaned out all that are good out of them; they would take all the golden and ſilver veſſels, veſſels of honour, and leave us none but wooden and ſtone, veſſels of diſhonour; and ſome are for ſeparation wholly, and ſo turne all the reſt over to Antichriſt; yea, ſome ſo violent, as that they would pluck downe our very meeting houſes (tropically called Churches) which they deride by the name of Steeple houſes; and all are in wayes of contention, ſo that we are like <hi>Sampſons</hi> foxes tyed together by the tayles with firebrands between them to burn up the ſtanding corn.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:123237:27"/>I ſhall conclude with an earneſt deſire of, and exhortation to unity and peace. The unity of the Church ſhould be a ſtrong mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to unity in judgement, heart, and way. It is that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle preſſeth <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.3, 4. <hi>Endeavouring to keep the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace, for there is one body, and one ſpirit,</hi> &amp;c. This ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall unity it is that Chriſt ſo earneſtly and often prayed for in that ſhort prayer, <hi>John</hi> 17.11, 21, 23. <hi>That they may be one as we are one. That they all may be one, that they alſo may be one in us. That they may be made perfect in one,</hi> And this was <hi>Pauls</hi> earneſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Now I beſeech you, brethren, by the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye all ſpeake the ſame thing, and that there be no diviſions among you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but that you be perfectly joyned together in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judgement.</hi> And again, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.11. it is one of the laſt things he concludes his Epiſtle with. <hi>Finally brethren, farewell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> be perfect, be of good comfort, be of one mind, live in peace, and the God of love and peace ſhall be with you.</hi> And <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.27. He preſſeth it as the only thing he deſired of them. <hi>Only let your converſation be as it becommeth the Gospell of Chriſt, that whether I come and ſee you, or elſe be abſent, I may heare of your affaires, that ye ſtand faſt in one ſpirit, with one mind, ſtriving together for the faith of the Gospell.</hi> Certainly unity of judgement is of more impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance then we are aware of, elſe the Apoſtle would not preſſe it with ſuch ſolemne adjurations, and intreaties, ſo often as he doth. Yea, when there were but two women that differed in opinion (as it is conceived) the Apoſtle thought it beſeeming apoſtolicall gravity, and the holy Ghoſt judged it meet for a piece of cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall Scripture to take notice of it, and compoſe it. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.2. <hi>I beſeech Enodias, and beſeech Syntiche, that they be of the ſame mind in the Lord.</hi> Though it might ſeeme but womens brabbles, yet we know how great a matter a little fire kindleth, a little ſtrife and errour will encreaſe to more ungodlineſſe.</p>
            <p>Conſider we, that there is but one truth, and that is of God, and God is truth, and errour is of the Devill.</p>
            <p>Conſider that the underſtanding is the higheſt and foremoſt faculty of the ſoule, it is as the fore-horſe in the teame, the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding faculty, and as that is informed, ſo the will, and conſcience, and affections muſt needs worke, and follow that, and if that be lead into errour, it muſt neceſſarily miſ-leade the whole man.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:123237:28"/>Conſider that a chiefe part of the image of God in man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in knowledge, and ſo is upon the underſtanding, which by errour is defaced.</p>
            <p>Remember the ſolemne caveats given by the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. <hi>I beſeech you brethren, mark them which cauſe diviſions and offences contrary to the doctrine which ye have learned, and avoide them. For they that are ſuch, ſerve not our Lord Jeſus Christ, but their own belly, and by good words and bleſſed or faire ſpeeches deceive the hearts of the ſimple.</hi> And <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.14. <hi>That we henceforth be no more children toſſed to and fro, and carried about with every wind of doctrine by the ſleight of men, and cunning craftineſſe</hi> (or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the method of errour) <hi>whereby they lie in wait to deceive.</hi> Chriſt himſelfe tels us, that <hi>falſe Prophets ſhall come that ſhall deceive (if it were poſſible) the very elect. Behold, I have told you before, Matth.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>4.24, 25. And <hi>Paul</hi> tels us, <hi>Of your ſelves ſhall men ariſe ſpeaking perverſe things, to draw away diſciples after them. Therefore watch. Acts</hi> 20.30, 31. <hi>Therefore Hold fast the forme of ſound words, which thou haſt heard of me,</hi> 2 Tim. 1.13. They that coine new words and new high ſtrange expreſſions to amaze the people, it is a ſigne as <hi>Calvin</hi> tels us, that they have ſome new opinion upon the Anvill.</p>
            <p>O let us labour to be of one heart, ſeeing we are all but one body, and have but one head, and one ſpirit, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are all brethren of the ſame heavenly Father. This is that which God hath promiſed his people, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 11.19. <hi>I will give them one heart, and I will put a new ſpirit within you.</hi> And we find Chriſt inculcating this exhortation, <hi>John</hi> 13.34. <hi>A new Commandment I give unto you that ye love one another, as I have lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved you, that ye alſo love one another. By this ſhall all men know that ye are my diſciples if you have love one to another, John</hi> 13.34, 35. <hi>Againe, This is my commandment that ye love one another as I have loved you. John</hi> 15.12. <hi>And ver.</hi> 17. <hi>Theſe things I command you that you love one another.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 2.46.</note> And this we find practiſed, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.32. <hi>And the multitude of them that beleeved were of one heart and one ſoule.</hi> And this <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth to, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.10. <hi>Be kindly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctioned one to another with brotherly love, in honour preferring one another.</hi> And we find the unity both of judgement and heart ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted unto, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Finally be ye all of one mind, having com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:123237:28"/>
one of another, love as brethren, be pitifull, be courteus.</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions is the Devils muſick, but that which makes the Devill laugh, ſhould make us cry. O what a ſolemne obſecration is that of <hi>Paul, Phil.</hi> 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, 2. <hi>If there be any conſolation in Christ, if any comfort of love, if any fellowſhip of the Spirit, if any bowels and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; fulfill ye my joy that ye be like minded, having the ſame love, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of one accord, of one mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O that we might labour to be of one way alſo. This is that which God hath promiſed his people, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.39. <hi>I will give them one heart and one way, that they may feare me for ever, for the good of them and of their Children after them.</hi> And <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Then will I turne to the people a pure language, that they may all call upon the name of the Lord with one conſent</hi> or one ſhoulder. And this was the bleſſing to <hi>Hezekiah</hi> in his people, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30.12. <hi>Alſo in</hi> Judah <hi>the hand of God was to give them one heart to doe the Commandement of the King and of the Princes, by the word of the Lord.</hi> Certainly there is but one rule for Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline. <hi>And as many as walke according to this rule, peace be on them and on the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell of God. Gal.</hi> 6.16. And this is the Apoſtles exhortation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.6. <hi>That ye may with one mind and one mouth glorify God.</hi> Yea though we be not of the ſame judgement in every thing, yet as it is <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.16. <hi>whereto we have already attained. Let us walke by the ſame rule, let us mind the ſame things.</hi> And this unity in way is that which we have ſworn unto, and covenanted in our late Nationall League and Covenant, in the firſt branch of it. That we ſhall endeavour to bring the Churches of God in the three Kingdomes of <hi>England Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> to the neereſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction and uniformity in Religion, Confeſſion of faith, Form of Church Government, Directory for Worſhip and Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; That we and our poſterity after us may as brethren live in faith and love, and the Lord may delight to dwell in the midſt of us. And we ſhall be forſworne if we endeavour it not. All the members of the ſame body naturall agree to go the ſame way. Yea the ſtrength, health, and beauty of the body naturall conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in the faſt knitting of all the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers together to each other, and to the head, and the luxation therof is dangerous: ſo and much more it is in a body Politike or Eccleſiaſticall. And though the diviſions in our civill eſtate be very ſad, and might deſerve teares
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:123237:29"/>
of bloud to bewaile them, yet I looke upon diviſions in the Church as a matter of more fad and dolefull conſequence, and I feare, (but wiſh I might be miſtaken) that when the breaches of the common wealth ſhall be cloſed, the breaches in the Church may grow wider, and the differences riſe higher; which having ſeazed upon the underſtandings and conſciences of men cannot be compoſed by commands nor clubbed down by force. Only here is my hope herein, that he which found a way to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile God and man when they were at enmity, can find a way to reconcile man and man though they be at difference. <hi>Now the God of peace that brought againe from the dead our Lord Ieſus Christ,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13.20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>that great Shepheard of the ſheep, through the bloud of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Covenant, make us perfect in every good worke to do his will, working in us that which is well pleaſing in his ſight, through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, to whom be glory for ever and ever, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
